Appendix D. Release Notes
Prev  |   |

Appendix D. Release Notes

Table of Contents

Release 25.05
Release 24.11
Release 24.05
Release 23.11
Release 23.05
Release 22.11
Release 22.05
Release 21.11
Release 21.05
Release 20.09
Release 20.03
Release 19.09
Release 19.03
Release 18.09

This section lists the release notes for stable versions of Home Manager and the current unstable version.

Release 25.05

Table of Contents

Highlights
State Version Changes

This is the current unstable branch and the information in this section is therefore not final.

Highlights

This release has the following notable changes:

The systemd.user.startServices option now defaults to true, meaning that services will automatically be restarted as needed when activating a configuration.

Further, the "legacy" alternative has been removed and will now result in an evaluation error if used.

The "suggest" alternative will remain for a while longer but may also be deprecated for removal in the future.

The Home Manager test suite has been removed from the main Nix Flake since it caused unnecessary evaluations and downloads. Instead the tests are available through a Nix Flake file inside the tests directory. See the section called “Tests” for example commands.

State Version Changes

The state version in this release includes the changes below. These changes are only active if the home.stateVersion option is set to "25.05" or later.

No changes.

Release 24.11

Table of Contents

Highlights
State Version Changes

The 24.11 release branch became stable in November, 2024.

Highlights

This release has the following notable changes:

The swayidle module behavior has changed. Specifically, swayidle was previously always called with a -w flag. This flag is now moved to the default services.swayidle.extraArgs value to make it optional.

Your configuration may break if you already set this option and also rely on the flag being automatically added. To resolve this, please add -w to your assignment of services.swayidle.extraArgs.

Support for Boolean values in the option programs.eza.icons is deprecated for future removal. The new value for true is "auto", and for false it is null.

State Version Changes

The state version in this release includes the changes below. These changes are only active if the home.stateVersion option is set to "24.11" or later.

There was no state version change in this release.

Release 24.05

Table of Contents

Highlights
State Version Changes

The 24.05 release branch became stable in May, 2024.

Highlights

This release has the following notable changes:

The .release file in the Home Manager project root has been removed. Please use the release.json file instead.

The home-manager uninstall command has been reworked to, hopefully, be more robust. The new implementation makes use of a new Boolean configuration option uninstall that can also be used in a pure Nix Flake setup.

Specifically, if you are using a Flake only installation, then you can clean up a Home Manager installation by adding

uninstall = true;

to your existing configuration and then build and activate. This will override any other configuration and cause, for example, the removal of all managed files.

Please be very careful when enabling this option since activating the built configuration will not only remove the managed files but all Home Manager state from your user environment. This includes removing all your historic Home Manager generations!

The use of $DRY_RUN_CMD and $DRY_RUN_NULL in activation script blocks is now deprecated. Instead use the new shell function run. In most cases it is sufficient to replace $DRY_RUN_CMD by run. For example, if your configuration currently contains

home.activation.reportChanges = config.lib.dag.entryAnywhere ''
  if [[ -v oldGenPath ]]; then
    $DRY_RUN_CMD nix store diff-closures $oldGenPath $newGenPath
  fi
'';

then you are now encouraged to change to

home.activation.reportChanges = config.lib.dag.entryAnywhere ''
  if [[ -v oldGenPath ]]; then
    run nix store diff-closures $oldGenPath $newGenPath
  fi
'';

See the description of home.activation for more. The deprecated variables will continue to work for now but their use may in the future trigger a warning message and eventually they may be removed entirely.

Similarly, the use of $VERBOSE_ECHO in activation script blocks is deprecated. Instead use the new shell function verboseEcho. That is,

home.activation.doThing = config.lib.dag.entryAnywhere ''
  $VERBOSE_ECHO "Doing the thing"
''

should now be expressed

home.activation.doThing = config.lib.dag.entryAnywhere ''
  verboseEcho "Doing the thing"
''

See the description of home.activation for more. The deprecated variable will continue to work for now but its use may in the future trigger a warning message and eventually it may be removed entirely.

State Version Changes

The state version in this release includes the changes below. These changes are only active if the home.stateVersion option is set to "24.05" or later.

There was no state version change in this release.

Release 23.11

Table of Contents

Highlights
State Version Changes

The 23.11 release branch became stable in November, 2023.

Highlights

This release has the following notable changes:

When using programs.fish.enable, the setup code for home.sessionVariables is now translated with babelfish. This should result in significantly faster shell startup times but could theoretically break if you have very complex bash expressions in a session variable. Please report any issues you experience.

The .release file in the Home Manager source tree has been supplanted by release.json, which contains more information about the branch. If you have any external code reading this file, please switch to consuming release.json instead. The .release file will be removed in 24.05.

Home Manager has migrated to using the upstream Nixpkgs lib.nixosOptionsDoc processor for option documentation. If you have any external Home Manager modules, their option descriptions and literal examples should be translated to Nixpkgs-flavoured Markdown.

The services.password-store-sync module has been removed. Use services.git-sync instead.

State Version Changes

The state version in this release includes the changes below. These changes are only active if the home.stateVersion option is set to "23.11" or later.

Nothing, yet.

Release 23.05

Table of Contents

Highlights
State Version Changes

The 23.05 release branch became the stable branch in May, 2023.

Highlights

This release has the following notable changes:

Firefox add-ons are now managed per-profile. That is, if you are currently having

programs.firefox.extensions = [ foo bar ];

in your configuration then you must change it to

programs.firefox.profiles.myprofile.extensions = [ foo bar ];

The default configuration location has been changed from ~/.config/nixpkgs/home.nix to ~/.config/home-manager/home.nix.

Similarly, if you are using a Nix flake based setup then the default flake file location has changed from ~/.config/nixpkgs/flake.nix to ~/.config/home-manager/flake.nix.

The old location will continue to work but using it will trigger a warning message. We changed the default configuration location to avoid confusion about which files belong to Home Manager and which belong to Nixpkgs.

The home-manager tool now offers an init command. This command can be used to generate an initial Home Manager configuration, and optionally also activate it. The recommended installation method for a standalone Home Manager setup with Nix flakes uses this new command. The standard installation method remains the same but uses the new command internally. See sec-flakes-standalone for more.

State Version Changes

The state version in this release includes the changes below. These changes are only active if the home.stateVersion option is set to "23.05" or later.

The options

xsession.windowManager.i3.config.window.titlebar

xsession.windowManager.i3.config.floating.titlebar

wayland.windowManager.sway.config.window.titlebar

wayland.windowManager.sway.config.floating.titlebar

now default to true which is consistent with the default values for those options used by i3 and sway.

Release 22.11

Table of Contents

Highlights
State Version Changes

The 22.11 release branch became the stable branch in November, 2022.

Highlights

This release has the following notable changes:

The home.stateVersion option no longer has a default value. It used to default to “18.09”, which was the Home Manager version that introduced the option. If your configuration does not explicitly set this option then you need to add

home.stateVersion = "18.09";

to your configuration.

The Flake function homeManagerConfiguration has been simplified. Specifically, the arguments

configuration,

username,

homeDirectory,

stateVersion,

extraModules, and

system

have been removed. Instead use the new modules argument, which accepts a list of NixOS modules.

Further, the pkgs argument is now mandatory and should be set to nixpkgs.legacyPackages.${system} where nixpkgs is the Nixpkgs input of your choice.

For example, if your Flake currently contains

homeManagerConfiguration {
  configuration = import ./home.nix;
  system = "x86_64-linux";
  username = "jdoe";
  homeDirectory = "/home/jdoe";
  stateVersion = "22.05";
  extraModules = [ ./some-extra-module.nix ];
}

then you can change it to

homeManagerConfiguration {
  pkgs = nixpkgs.legacyPackages.${system};
  modules = [
    ./home.nix
    ./some-extra-module.nix
    {
      home = {
        username = "jdoe";
        homeDirectory = "/home/jdoe";
        stateVersion = "22.05";
      };
    }
  ];
}

Of course, you can move the assignment of home.username, home.stateVersion to some other file or simply place them in your home.nix.

The services.picom module has been refactored to use structural settings.

As a result services.picom.extraOptions has been removed in favor of services.picom.settings. Also, services.picom.blur* were removed since upstream changed the blur settings to be more flexible. You can migrate the blur settings to use services.picom.settings instead.

The services.compton module has been removed. It was deprecated in release 20.03. Use services.picom instead.

State Version Changes

The state version in this release includes the changes below. These changes are only active if the home.stateVersion option is set to "22.11" or later.

The services.mpd.musicDirectory option now defaults to the value of xdg.userDirs.music if xdg.userDirs.enable is enabled. Otherwise it is undefined and must be specified in the user configuration.

The activation script now resets PATH before running. Before, the user’s PATH environment variable would be used in the script and this made it possible for commands in the activation script to run arbitrary commands accessible to the user. We now restrict the activation script to commands that are explicitly specified.

There is no official way to restore the old behavior. We attempt to make the activation script as reproducible as possible and honoring the user’s PATH reduces reproducibility.

If you need to run a command in an activation script block then refer to the command by its absolute command path, such as ${pkgs.hello}/bin/hello.

Release 22.05

Table of Contents

Highlights
State Version Changes

The 22.05 release branch became the stable branch in May, 2022.

Highlights

This release has the following notable changes:

The programs.waybar.settings.modules option was removed. Waybar modules should now be declared directly under programs.waybar.settings.

Home Manager now partially support translation of texts into different languages. Note, the support is quite limited at the moment. Specifically, it only applies to parts of the system written in the Bash language, such as the home-manager command line tool and the activation script.

If you would like to contribute to the translation effort then you can do so through the Home Manager Weblate project.

A new module, launchd.agents was added. Use this to enable services based on macOS LaunchAgents.

State Version Changes

The state version in this release includes the changes below. These changes are only active if the home.stateVersion option is set to "22.05" or later.

The programs.waybar.settings option now allows defining modules directly under programs.waybar.settings. Defining modules under programs.waybar.settings.modules will now be an error. For example,

programs.waybar.settings.modules."custom/my-module" = { };

becomes

programs.waybar.settings."custom/my-module" = { };

Release 21.11

Table of Contents

Highlights
State Version Changes

The 21.11 release branch became the stable branch in November, 2021.

Highlights

This release has the following notable changes:

All Home Manager modules are now loaded on all platforms. With this change you will get a more descriptive error message if you attempt to enable a module that is incompatible with the host platform.

Previously, modules that were platform specific would only be loaded on that particular platform. For example, a module defining a systemd service would only be loaded when the host platform was Linux. This reduced evaluation times, simplified the generated documentation, and made it impossible to accidentally use modules that do not support the host platform.

While the above benefits are quite nice, avoiding module loads also brings a few problems. For example, the public documentation will only show the options available for Linux hosts and the documentation cannot make references to options within modules that are unavailable on some hosts. Finally, users who wish to use the same configuration file for different platforms cannot do so, even if the platform incompatible options are unused.

Ultimately, the benefits of loading all modules won and the behavior has now changed. For associated discussion see issue #1906.

Rofi version 1.7.0 removed many options that were used by the module and replaced them with custom themes, which are more flexible and powerful.

You can replicate your old configuration by moving those options to programs.rofi.theme. Keep in mind that the syntax is different so you may need to do some changes.

Taskwarrior version 2.6.0 respects XDG Specification for the config file now. Option programs.taskwarrior.config and friends now generate the config file at $XDG_CONFIG_HOME/task/taskrc instead of ~/.taskrc.

State Version Changes

The state version in this release includes the changes below. These changes are only active if the home.stateVersion option is set to "21.11" or later.

The home.keyboard option now defaults to null, meaning that Home Manager won’t do any keyboard layout management. For example, setxkbmap won’t be run in X sessions.

The programs.pet.settings option no longer place its value inside a General attribute. For example,

programs.pet.settings.editor = "nvim";

becomes

programs.pet.settings.General.editor = "nvim";

The programs.waybar.settings option now allows defining modules directly under programs.waybar.settings. For example,

programs.waybar.settings.modules."custom/my-module" = { };

becomes

programs.waybar.settings."custom/my-module" = { };

Release 21.05

Table of Contents

Highlights
State Version Changes

The 21.05 release branch became the stable branch in May, 2021.

Highlights

This release has the following notable changes:

The ‘opt-programs.broot.verbs` option is now a list rather than an attribute set. To migrate, move the keys of the attrset into the list items’ invocation keys. For example,

programs.broot.verbs = {
  "p" = { execution = ":parent"; };
};

becomes

programs.broot.verbs = [
  {
    invocation = "p";
    execution = ":parent";
  }
];

The programs.mpv.package option has been changed to allow custom derivations. The following configuration is now possible:

programs.mpv.package = (pkgs.wrapMpv (pkgs.mpv-unwrapped.override {
  vapoursynthSupport = true;
}) {
  extraMakeWrapperArgs = [
    "--prefix" "LD_LIBRARY_PATH" ":" "${pkgs.vapoursynth-mvtools}/lib/vapoursynth"
  ];
});

As a result of this change, programs.mpv.package is no longer the resulting derivation. Use the newly introduced programs.mpv.finalPackage instead.

The programs.rofi.extraConfig option is now an attribute set rather than a string. To migrate, move each line into the attribute set, removing the rofi. prefix from the keys. For example,

programs.rofi.extraConfig = ''
  rofi.show-icons: true
  rofi.modi: drun,emoji,ssh
'';

becomes

programs.rofi.extraConfig = {
  show-icons = true;
  modi = "drun,emoji,ssh";
};

The programs.rofi.theme option now supports defining a theme using an attribute set, the following configuration is now possible:

programs.rofi.theme = let
  # Necessary to avoid quoting non-string values
  inherit (config.lib.formats.rasi) mkLiteral;
in {
   "@import" = "~/.config/rofi/theme.rasi";

  "*" = {
    background-color = mkLiteral "#000000";
    foreground-color = mkLiteral "rgba ( 250, 251, 252, 100 % )";
    border-color = mkLiteral "#FFFFFF";
    width = 512;
  };

  "#textbox-prompt-colon" = {
    expand = false;
    str = ":";
    margin = mkLiteral "0px 0.3em 0em 0em";
    text-color = mkLiteral "@foreground-color";
  };
};

The services.redshift.extraOptions and services.gammastep.extraOptions options were removed in favor of services.redshift.settings and services.gammastep.settings, that are now an attribute set rather than a string. They also support new features not available before, for example:

services.redshift = {
  dawnTime = "6:00-7:45";
  duskTime = "18:35-20:15";
  settings = {
    redshift = {
      gamma = 0.8;
      adjustment-method = "randr";
    };

    randr = {
      screen = 0;
    };
  };
};

It is recommended to check either redshift.conf.sample or gammastep.conf.sample for the available additional options in each program.

Specifying programs.neomutt.binds.map or programs.neomutt.macros.map as a single string is now deprecated in favor of specfiying it as a list of strings.

The programs.neovim.configure is deprecated in favor of other programs.neovim options; please use the other options at your disposal:

configure.packages.*.opt  -> programs.neovim.plugins = [ { plugin = ...; optional = true; }]
configure.packages.*.start  -> programs.neovim.plugins = [ { plugin = ...; }]
configure.customRC -> programs.neovim.extraConfig

Home Manager now respects the NO_COLOR environment variable as per https://no-color.org/.

Qt module now supports qt.style.name to specify a theme name and qt.style.package to specify a theme package. If you have set qt.platformTheme to gnome, a qt.style.package compatible with both Qt and Gtk is now required to be set. For instance:

qt = {
  platformTheme = "gnome";
  style = {
    name = "adwaita-dark";
    package = pkgs.adwaita-qt;
  };
};

The library type fontType now has a size attribute in addition to name. For example:

font = {
  name = "DejaVu Sans";
  size = 8;
};

The programs.htop.settings option is introduced to replace individual options in programs.htop. To migrate, set the htop options directly in programs.htop.settings. For example:

programs.htop = {
  enabled = true;
  settings = {
     color_scheme = 5;
     delay = 15;
     highlight_base_name = 1;
     highlight_megabytes = 1;
     highlight_threads = 1;
  };
};

State Version Changes

The state version in this release includes the changes below. These changes are only active if the home.stateVersion option is set to "21.05" or later.

The newsboat module now stores generated configuration in $XDG_CONFIG_HOME/newsboat.

Release 20.09

Table of Contents

Highlights
State Version Changes

The 20.09 release branch became the stable branch in late September, 2020.

Highlights

This release has the following notable changes:

Nothing has happened.

State Version Changes

The state version in this release includes the changes below. These changes are only active if the home.stateVersion option is set to "20.09" or later.

The options home.homeDirectory and home.username no longer have default values and must therefore be provided in your configuration. Previously their values would default to the content of the environment variables HOME and USER, respectively.

Further, the options xdg.cacheHome, xdg.dataHome will no longer be affected by the XDG_CACHE_HOME, XDG_CONFIG_HOME, and XDG_DATA_HOME environment variables. They now unconditionally default to

"${config.home.homeDirectory}/.cache",

"${config.home.homeDirectory}/.config", and

"${config.home.homeDirectory}/.local/share".

If you choose to switch to state version 20.09 then you must set these options if you use non-default XDG base directory paths.

The initial configuration generated by

$ nix-shell '<home-manager>' -A install

will automatically include these options, when necessary.

Git’s smtpEncryption option is now set to tls only if both accounts.email.accounts.name.smtp.tls.enable and accounts.email.accounts.name.smtp.tls.useStartTls are true. If only accounts.email.accounts.name.smtp.tls.enable is true, ssl is used instead.

The nixpkgs module no longer references <nixpkgs>. Before it would do so when building the pkgs module argument. Starting with state version 20.09, the pkgs argument is instead built from the same Nixpkgs that was used to initialize the Home Manager modules. This is useful, for example, when using Home Manager within a Nix Flake. If you want to keep using <nixpkgs> with state version ≥ 20.09 then add

_module.args.pkgsPath = <nixpkgs>;

to your Home Manager configuration.

The options wayland.windowManager.sway.config.bars and opt-xsession.windowManager.i3.config.bars have been changed so that most of the suboptions are now nullable and default to null. The default for these two options has been changed to manually set the old defaults for each suboption. The overall effect is that if the bars options is not set, then the default remains the same. On the other hand, something like:

bars = [ {
  command = "waybar";
} ];

will now create the config:

bar {
  swaybar_command waybar
}

instead of

bar {

  font pango:monospace 8
  mode dock
  hidden_state hide
  position bottom
  status_command /nix/store/h7s6i9q1z5fxrlyyw5ls8vqxhf5bcs5a-i3status-2.13/bin/i3status
  swaybar_command waybar
  workspace_buttons yes
  strip_workspace_numbers no
  tray_output primary
  colors {
    background #000000
    statusline #ffffff
    separator #666666
    focused_workspace #4c7899 #285577 #ffffff
    active_workspace #333333 #5f676a #ffffff
    inactive_workspace #333333 #222222 #888888
    urgent_workspace #2f343a #900000 #ffffff
    binding_mode #2f343a #900000 #ffffff
  }

}

Release 20.03

Table of Contents

Highlights
State Version Changes

The 20.03 release branch became the stable branch in April, 2020.

Highlights

This release has the following notable changes:

Assigning a list to the home.file, xdg.dataFile options is now deprecated and will produce a warning message if used. Specifically, if your configuration currently contains something like

home.file = [
  {
    target = ".config/foo.txt";
    text = "bar";
  }
]

then it should be updated to instead use the equivalent attribute set form

home.file = {
  ".config/foo.txt".text = "bar";
}

Support for the list form will be removed in Home Manager version 20.09.

The lib function attribute given to modules is now enriched with an attribute hm containing extra library functions specific for Home Manager. More specifically, lib.hm is now the same as config.lib and should be the preferred choice since it is more robust.

Therefore, if your configuration makes use of, for example, config.lib.dag to create activation script blocks, it is recommended to change to lib.hm.dag.

Note, in the unlikely case that you are

using Home Manager’s NixOS or nix-darwin module,

have made your own Home Manager module containing an top-level option named config or options, and

assign to this option in your system configuration inside a plain attribute set, i.e., without a function argument,

then you must update your configuration to perform the option assignment inside a config attribute. For example, instead of

home-manager.users.jane = { config = "foo"; };

use

home-manager.users.jane = { config.config = "foo"; };

The services.compton module has been deprecated and instead the new module services.picom should be used. This is because Nixpkgs no longer packages compton, and instead packages the (mostly) compatible fork called picom.

The list form of the programs.ssh.matchBlocks option has been deprecated and configurations requiring match blocks in a defined order should switch to using DAG entries instead. For example, a configuration

programs.ssh.matchBlocks = [
  {
    host = "alpha.foo.com";
    user = "jd";
  }
  {
    host = "*.foo.com";
    user = "john.doe";
  }
];

can be expressed along the lines of

programs.ssh.matchBlocks = {
  "*.example.com" = {
    user = "john.doe";
  }
  "alpha.example.com" = lib.hm.dag.entryBefore ["*.example.com"] {
    user = "jd";
  }
};

Support for the list form will be removed in Home Manager version 20.09.

State Version Changes

The state version in this release includes the changes below. These changes are only active if the home.stateVersion option is set to "20.03" or later.

The programs.zsh.history.path option is no longer prepended by $HOME, which allows specifying absolute paths, for example, using the xdg module. Also, the default value is fixed to $HOME/.zsh_history and dotDir path is not prepended to it anymore.

The newsboat module will now default in displaying queries before urls in its main window. This makes sense in the case when one has a lot of URLs and few queries.

Release 19.09

Table of Contents

Highlights
State Version Changes

The 19.09 release branch became the stable branch in October, 2019.

Highlights

This release has the following notable changes:

The programs.firefox.enableGoogleTalk and programs.firefox.enableIcedTea options are now deprecated and will only work if Firefox ESR 52.x is used.

The home-manager tool now provides an uninstall sub-command that can be used to uninstall Home Manager, if used in the standalone mode. That is, not as a NixOS module.

State Version Changes

The state version in this release includes the changes below. These changes are only active if the home.stateVersion option is set to "19.09" or later.

The programs.firefox.package option now expects a wrapped Firefox package and defaults to pkgs.firefox.

The options home.keyboard.layout and home.keyboard.variant now default to null, which indicates that the system value should be used.

Release 19.03

Table of Contents

Highlights
State Version Changes

The 19.03 release branch became the stable branch in April, 2019.

Highlights

This release has the following notable changes:

The home.file.name.source option now allows source files to be hidden, that is, having a name starting with the . character. It also allows the source file name to contain characters not typically allowed for Nix store paths. For example, your configuration can now contain things such as

home.file."my file".source = ./. + "/file with spaces!";

The type used for the systemd unit options under systemd.user.sockets, etc. has been changed to offer more robust merging of configurations. If you don’t override values within systemd units then you are not affected by this change. Unfortunately, if you do override unit values you may encounter errors.

In particular, if you get an error saying that a “unique option” is “defined multiple times” then you need to use the mkForce function. For example,

systemd.user.services.foo.Service.ExecStart = "/foo/bar";

becomes

systemd.user.services.foo.Service.ExecStart = lib.mkForce "/foo/bar";

We had to make this change because the old merging was causing too many confusing situations for people.

State Version Changes

The state version in this release includes the changes below. These changes are only active if the home.stateVersion option is set to “19.03” or later.

There is now an option programs.beets.enable that defaults to false. Before the module would be active if the programs.beets.settings option was non-empty.

Release 18.09

The 18.09 release branch became the stable branch in September, 2018.

Prev  |   |
Appendix C. nix-darwin Configuration Options  | Home |

Home Manager Manual
  |   |  Next

Home Manager Manual

Version 26.05 (unstable)

Table of Contents

Preface
Introduction to Home Manager
Installing Home Manager

Standalone installation
NixOS module
nix-darwin module

Using Home Manager

Configuration Example
Rollbacks
Keeping your ~ safe from harm
Graphical services
GPU on non-NixOS systems
Modular Services
Updating
Upgrading to a new Home Manager release

Nix Flakes

Prerequisites
Standalone setup
NixOS module
nix-darwin module
flake-parts module

Writing Home Manager Modules

Option Types

Contributing

Getting started
Guidelines
News
Tests

Home Manager Internals

Activation

Third-Party Tools and Extensions

Module Collections

Frequently Asked Questions (FAQ)

Why is there a collision error when switching generation?
Why are the session variables not set?
How to set up a configuration for multiple users/machines?
Why do I get an error message about ca.desrt.dconf or dconf.service?
How do I install packages from Nixpkgs unstable?
How do I change the package used by a module?

A. Home Manager Configuration Options
B. NixOS Configuration Options
C. nix-darwin Configuration Options
D. Release Notes

List of Examples

1. Home Manager Rollback

Preface

This manual will eventually describe how to install, use, and extend Home Manager.

If you encounter problems then please reach out on the IRC channel #home-manager hosted by OFTC. There is also a Matrix room, which is bridged to the IRC channel. If your problem is caused by a bug in Home Manager then it should be reported on the Home Manager issue tracker.

Note

Commands prefixed with $ sudo have to be run as root, either requiring to login as root user or temporarily switching to it using sudo for example.

Introduction to Home Manager

Home Manager is a Nix-powered tool for reproducible management of the contents of users’ home directories. This includes programs, configuration files, environment variables and, well… arbitrary files. The following example snippet of Nix code:

programs.git = {
  enable = true;
  userEmail = "joe@example.org";
  userName = "joe";
};

would make available to a user the git executable and man pages and a configuration file ~/.config/git/config:

[user]
	email = "joe@example.org"
	name = "joe"

Since Home Manager is implemented in Nix, it provides several benefits:

Contents are reproducible — a home will be the exact same every time it is built, unless of course, an intentional change is made. This also means you can have the exact same home on different hosts.

Significantly faster and more powerful than various backup strategies.

Unlike “dotfiles” repositories, Home Manager supports specifying programs, as well as their configurations.

Supported by http://cache.nixos.org/, so that you don’t have to build from source.

If you do want to build some programs from source, there is hardly a tool more useful than Nix for that, and the build instructions can be neatly integrated in your Home Manager usage.

Infinitely composable, so that values in different configuration files and build instructions can share a source of truth.

Connects you with the most extensive and most up-to-date software package repository on earth, Nixpkgs.

Installing Home Manager

Home Manager can be used in three primary ways:

Using the standalone home-manager tool. For platforms other than NixOS and Darwin, this is the only available choice. It is also recommended for people on NixOS or Darwin that want to manage their home directory independently of the system as a whole. See Standalone installation for instructions on how to perform this installation.

As a module within a NixOS system configuration. This allows the user profiles to be built together with the system when running nixos-rebuild. See NixOS module for a description of this setup.

As a module within a nix-darwin system configuration. This allows the user profiles to be built together with the system when running darwin-rebuild. See nix-darwin module for a description of this setup.

Note

In this chapter we describe how to install Home Manager in the standard way using channels. If you prefer to use Nix Flakes then please see the instructions in nix flakes.

Table of Contents

Standalone installation
NixOS module
nix-darwin module

Standalone installation

Make sure you have a working Nix installation. Specifically, make sure that your user is able to build and install Nix packages. For example, you should be able to successfully run a command like nix-instantiate '<nixpkgs>' -A hello without having to switch to the root user. For a multi-user install of Nix this means that your user must be covered by the allowed-users Nix option. On NixOS you can control this option using the nix.settings.allowed-users system option.

Add the appropriate Home Manager channel. If you are following Nixpkgs master or an unstable channel you can run

$ nix-channel --add https://github.com/nix-community/home-manager/archive/master.tar.gz home-manager
$ nix-channel --update

and if you follow a Nixpkgs version 25.11 channel you can run

$ nix-channel --add https://github.com/nix-community/home-manager/archive/release-25.11.tar.gz home-manager
$ nix-channel --update

Run the Home Manager installation command and create the first Home Manager generation:

$ nix-shell '<home-manager>' -A install

Once finished, Home Manager should be active and available in your user environment.

If you do not plan on having Home Manager manage your shell configuration then you must source the

$HOME/.nix-profile/etc/profile.d/hm-session-vars.sh

file in your shell configuration. Alternatively source

/etc/profiles/per-user/$USER/etc/profile.d/hm-session-vars.sh

when managing home configuration together with system configuration.

This file can be sourced directly by POSIX.2-like shells such as Bash or Z shell. Fish users can use utilities such as foreign-env or babelfish.

For example, if you use Bash then add

. "$HOME/.nix-profile/etc/profile.d/hm-session-vars.sh"

to your ~/.profile file.

If instead of using channels you want to run Home Manager from a Git checkout of the repository then you can use the home-manager.path option to specify the absolute path to the repository.

Once installed you can see Using Home Manager for a more detailed description of Home Manager and how to use it.

NixOS module

Home Manager provides a NixOS module that allows you to prepare user environments directly from the system configuration file, which often is more convenient than using the home-manager tool. It also opens up additional possibilities, for example, to automatically configure user environments in NixOS declarative containers or on systems deployed through NixOps.

To make the NixOS module available for use you must import it into your system configuration. This is most conveniently done by adding a Home Manager channel to the root user. For example, if you are following Nixpkgs master or an unstable channel, you can run

$ sudo nix-channel --add https://github.com/nix-community/home-manager/archive/master.tar.gz home-manager
$ sudo nix-channel --update

and if you follow a Nixpkgs version 25.11 channel, you can run

$ sudo nix-channel --add https://github.com/nix-community/home-manager/archive/release-25.11.tar.gz home-manager
$ sudo nix-channel --update

It is then possible to add

imports = [ <home-manager/nixos> ];

to your system configuration.nix file, which will introduce a new NixOS option called home-manager.users whose type is an attribute set that maps user names to Home Manager configurations.

Alternatively, home-manager installation can be done declaratively through configuration.nix using the following syntax:

{ config, pkgs, lib, ... }:

let
  home-manager = builtins.fetchTarball https://github.com/nix-community/home-manager/archive/release-25.11.tar.gz;
in
{
  imports =
    [
      (import "${home-manager}/nixos")
    ];

  users.users.eve.isNormalUser = true;
  home-manager.users.eve = { pkgs, ... }: {
    home.packages = [ pkgs.atool pkgs.httpie ];
    programs.bash.enable = true;

    # The state version is required and should stay at the version you
    # originally installed.
    home.stateVersion = "25.11";
  };
}

For example, a NixOS configuration may include the lines

users.users.eve.isNormalUser = true;
home-manager.users.eve = { pkgs, ... }: {
  home.packages = [ pkgs.atool pkgs.httpie ];
  programs.bash.enable = true;

  # This value determines the Home Manager release that your configuration is
  # compatible with. This helps avoid breakage when a new Home Manager release
  # introduces backwards incompatible changes.
  #
  # You should not change this value, even if you update Home Manager. If you do
  # want to update the value, then make sure to first check the Home Manager
  # release notes.
  home.stateVersion = "25.11"; # Please read the comment before changing. 

};

and after a sudo nixos-rebuild switch the user eve’s environment should include a basic Bash configuration and the packages atool and httpie.

Note

If nixos-rebuild switch does not result in the environment you expect, you can take a look at the output of the Home Manager activation script output using

$ systemctl status "home-manager-$USER.service"

If you do not plan on having Home Manager manage your shell configuration then you must add either

. "$HOME/.nix-profile/etc/profile.d/hm-session-vars.sh"

or

. "/etc/profiles/per-user/$USER/etc/profile.d/hm-session-vars.sh"

to your shell configuration, depending on whether home-manager.useUserPackages is enabled. This file can be sourced directly by POSIX.2-like shells such as Bash or Z shell. Fish users can use utilities such as foreign-env or babelfish.

Note

By default packages will be installed to $HOME/.nix-profile but they can be installed to /etc/profiles if

home-manager.useUserPackages = true;

is added to the system configuration. This is necessary if, for example, you wish to use nixos-rebuild build-vm. This option may become the default value in the future.

Note

By default, Home Manager uses a private pkgs instance that is configured via the home-manager.users.<name>.nixpkgs options. To instead use the global pkgs that is configured via the system level nixpkgs options, set

home-manager.useGlobalPkgs = true;

This saves an extra Nixpkgs evaluation, adds consistency, and removes the dependency on NIX_PATH, which is otherwise used for importing Nixpkgs.

Note

Home Manager will pass osConfig as a module argument to any modules you create. This contains the system’s NixOS configuration.

{ lib, pkgs, osConfig, ... }:

Once installed you can see Using Home Manager for a more detailed description of Home Manager and how to use it.

nix-darwin module

Home Manager provides a module that allows you to prepare user environments directly from the nix-darwin configuration file, which often is more convenient than using the home-manager tool.

To make the nix-darwin module available for use you must import it into your system configuration. This is most conveniently done by adding a Home Manager channel. For example, if you are following Nixpkgs master or an unstable channel, you can run

$ nix-channel --add https://github.com/nix-community/home-manager/archive/master.tar.gz home-manager
$ nix-channel --update

and if you follow a Nixpkgs version 25.11 channel, you can run

$ nix-channel --add https://github.com/nix-community/home-manager/archive/release-25.11.tar.gz home-manager
$ nix-channel --update

It is then possible to add

imports = [ <home-manager/nix-darwin> ];

to your nix-darwin configuration.nix file, which will introduce a home-manager.users option whose type is an attribute set that maps user names to Home Manager configurations.

For example, a nix-darwin configuration may include the lines

users.users.eve = {
  name = "eve";
  home = "/Users/eve";
};
home-manager.users.eve = { pkgs, ... }: {
  home.packages = [ pkgs.atool pkgs.httpie ];
  programs.bash.enable = true;

  # The state version is required and should stay at the version you
  # originally installed.
  home.stateVersion = "25.11";
};

and after a darwin-rebuild switch the user eve’s environment should include a basic Bash configuration and the packages atool and httpie.

If you do not plan on having Home Manager manage your shell configuration then you must add either

. "$HOME/.nix-profile/etc/profile.d/hm-session-vars.sh"

or

. "/etc/profiles/per-user/$USER/etc/profile.d/hm-session-vars.sh"

to your shell configuration, depending on whether home-manager.useUserPackages is enabled. This file can be sourced directly by POSIX.2-like shells such as Bash or Z shell. Fish users can use utilities such as foreign-env or babelfish.

Note

By default user packages will not be ignored in favor of environment.systemPackages, but they will be installed to /etc/profiles/per-user/$USERNAME if

home-manager.useUserPackages = true;

is added to the nix-darwin configuration. This option may become the default value in the future.

Note

By default, Home Manager uses a private pkgs instance that is configured via the home-manager.users.<name>.nixpkgs options. To instead use the global pkgs that is configured via the system level nixpkgs options, set

home-manager.useGlobalPkgs = true;

This saves an extra Nixpkgs evaluation, adds consistency, and removes the dependency on NIX_PATH, which is otherwise used for importing Nixpkgs.

Note

Home Manager will pass osConfig as a module argument to any modules you create. This contains the system’s nix-darwin configuration.

{ lib, pkgs, osConfig, ... }:

Once installed you can see Using Home Manager for a more detailed description of Home Manager and how to use it.

Using Home Manager

Your use of Home Manager is centered around the configuration file, which is typically found at ~/.config/home-manager/home.nix in the standard installation or ~/.config/home-manager/flake.nix in a Nix flake based installation.

Note

The default configuration used to be placed in ~/.config/nixpkgs¸ so you may see references to that elsewhere. The old directory still works but Home Manager will print a warning message when used.

This configuration file can be built and activated.

Building a configuration produces a directory in the Nix store that contains all files and programs that should be available in your home directory and Nix user profile, respectively. The build step also checks that the configuration is valid and it will fail with an error if you, for example, assign a value to an option that does not exist or assign a value of the wrong type. Some modules also have custom assertions that perform more detailed, module specific, checks.

Concretely, if your configuration contains

programs.emacs.enable = "yes";

then building it, for example using home-manager build, will result in an error message saying something like

$ home-manager build
error: A definition for option `programs.emacs.enable' is not of type `boolean'. Definition values:
- In `/home/jdoe/.config/home-manager/home.nix': "yes"
(use '--show-trace' to show detailed location information)

The message indicates that you must provide a Boolean value for this option, that is, either true or false. The documentation of each option will state the expected type, for programs.emacs.enable you will see “Type: boolean”. You there also find information about the default value and a description of the option. You can find the complete option documentation in Home Manager Configuration Options or directly in the terminal by running

man home-configuration.nix

Once a configuration is successfully built, it can be activated. The activation performs the steps necessary to make the files, programs, and services available in your user environment. The home-manager switch command performs a combined build and activation.

Table of Contents

Configuration Example
Rollbacks
Keeping your ~ safe from harm
Graphical services
GPU on non-NixOS systems
Modular Services
Updating
Upgrading to a new Home Manager release

Configuration Example

A fresh install of Home Manager will generate a minimal ~/.config/home-manager/home.nix file containing something like

{ config, pkgs, ... }:

{
  # Home Manager needs a bit of information about you and the
  # paths it should manage.
  home.username = "jdoe";
  home.homeDirectory = "/home/jdoe";

  # This value determines the Home Manager release that your
  # configuration is compatible with. This helps avoid breakage
  # when a new Home Manager release introduces backwards
  # incompatible changes.
  #
  # You can update Home Manager without changing this value. See
  # the Home Manager release notes for a list of state version
  # changes in each release.
  home.stateVersion = "25.11";

  # Let Home Manager install and manage itself.
  programs.home-manager.enable = true;
}

You can use this as a base for your further configurations.

Note

If you are not very familiar with the Nix language and NixOS modules then it is encouraged to start with small and simple changes. As you learn you can gradually grow the configuration with confidence.

As an example, let us expand the initial configuration file to also install the htop and fortune packages, install Emacs with a few extra packages available, and enable the user gpg-agent service.

To satisfy the above setup we should elaborate the home.nix file as follows:

{ config, pkgs, ... }:

{
  # Home Manager needs a bit of information about you and the
  # paths it should manage.
  home.username = "jdoe";
  home.homeDirectory = "/home/jdoe";

  # Packages that should be installed to the user profile.
  home.packages = [
    pkgs.htop
    pkgs.fortune
  ];

  # This value determines the Home Manager release that your
  # configuration is compatible with. This helps avoid breakage
  # when a new Home Manager release introduces backwards
  # incompatible changes.
  #
  # You can update Home Manager without changing this value. See
  # the Home Manager release notes for a list of state version
  # changes in each release.
  home.stateVersion = "25.11";

  # Let Home Manager install and manage itself.
  programs.home-manager.enable = true;

  programs.emacs = {
    enable = true;
    extraPackages = epkgs: [
      epkgs.nix-mode
      epkgs.magit
    ];
  };

  services.gpg-agent = {
    enable = true;
    defaultCacheTtl = 1800;
    enableSshSupport = true;
  };
}

Nixpkgs packages can be installed to the user profile using home.packages.

The option names of a program module typically start with programs.<package name>.

Similarly, for a service module, the names start with services.<package name>. Note in some cases a package has both programs and service options – Emacs is such an example.

To activate this configuration you can run

home-manager switch

or if you are not feeling so lucky,

home-manager build

which will create a result link to a directory containing an activation script and the generated home directory files.

Rollbacks

When you perform a home-manager switch and discover a problem then it is possible to roll back to the previous version of your configuration using home-manager switch --rollback. This will turn the previous configuration into the current configuration.

Example 1. Home Manager Rollback

Imagine you have just updated Nixpkgs and switched to a new Home Manager configuration. You discover that a package update included in your new configuration has a bug that was not present in the previous configuration.

You can then run home-manager switch --rollback to recover your previous configuration, which includes the working version of the package.

To see what happened above we can observe the list of Home Manager generations before and after the rollback:

$ home-manager generations
2024-01-04 11:56 : id 765 -> /nix/store/kahm1rxk77mnvd2l8pfvd4jkkffk5ijk-home-manager-generation (current)
2024-01-03 10:29 : id 764 -> /nix/store/2wsmsliqr5yynqkdyjzb1y57pr5q2lsj-home-manager-generation
2024-01-01 12:21 : id 763 -> /nix/store/mv960kl9chn2lal5q8lnqdp1ygxngcd1-home-manager-generation
2023-12-29 21:03 : id 762 -> /nix/store/6c0k1r03fxckql4vgqcn9ccb616ynb94-home-manager-generation
2023-12-25 18:51 : id 761 -> /nix/store/czc5y6vi1rvnkfv83cs3rn84jarcgsgh-home-manager-generation
…

$ home-manager switch --rollback
Starting home manager activation
…

$ home-manager generations
2024-01-04 11:56 : id 765 -> /nix/store/kahm1rxk77mnvd2l8pfvd4jkkffk5ijk-home-manager-generation
2024-01-03 10:29 : id 764 -> /nix/store/2wsmsliqr5yynqkdyjzb1y57pr5q2lsj-home-manager-generation (current)
2024-01-01 12:21 : id 763 -> /nix/store/mv960kl9chn2lal5q8lnqdp1ygxngcd1-home-manager-generation
2023-12-29 21:03 : id 762 -> /nix/store/6c0k1r03fxckql4vgqcn9ccb616ynb94-home-manager-generation
2023-12-25 18:51 : id 761 -> /nix/store/czc5y6vi1rvnkfv83cs3rn84jarcgsgh-home-manager-generation
…

Keeping your ~ safe from harm

Resolving file collisions
Advanced file behavior

To configure programs and services Home Manager must write various things to your home directory. To prevent overwriting any existing files when switching to a new generation, Home Manager will attempt to detect collisions between existing files and generated files. If any such collision is detected the activation will terminate before changing anything on your computer.

For example, suppose you have a wonderful, painstakingly created ~/.config/git/config and add

{
  # …

  programs.git = {
    enable = true;
    userName = "Jane Doe";
    userEmail = "jane.doe@example.org";
  };

  # …
}

to your configuration. Attempting to switch to the generation will then result in

$ home-manager switch
…
Activating checkLinkTargets
Existing file '/home/jdoe/.config/git/config' is in the way
Please move the above files and try again

This error is about a file that Home Manager wants to manage as a symbolic link in your home directory. It is separate from package profile collisions, which usually mention installPackages or a collision between .../bin/... path. For package collisions, see Why is there a collision error when switching generation?.

Resolving file collisions

The safest resolution is to inspect the existing path, move any settings you want Home Manager to manage into your configuration, and remove or move the unmanaged file before switching again.

For a standalone Home Manager installation, you can ask Home Manager to move unmanaged non-symlink paths out of the way during activation:

home-manager switch -b backup

With the command above, a colliding ~/.config/git/config is moved to ~/.config/git/config.backup before Home Manager links the managed file. If the backup path already exists then activation still aborts, so choose an extension whose backup path does not already exist.

Standalone activation can also run a custom command for each collision:

home-manager switch -B trash-put

The command receives the colliding path as an argument and must move or remove that path. If both -B and -b are set, the custom command takes precedence; the command may still use the HOME_MANAGER_BACKUP_EXT environment variable set by -b.

When Home Manager is used as a NixOS or nix-darwin module, configure the corresponding module options instead of passing standalone command line flags:

{
  home-manager.backupFileExtension = "backup";
}

or

{
  home-manager.backupCommand = "${pkgs.trash-cli}/bin/trash-put";
}

If both home-manager.backupCommand and home-manager.backupFileExtension are set, the command takes precedence. The extension is still exported to the command as HOME_MANAGER_BACKUP_EXT, so the command can use it when implementing its own backup naming. With home-manager.backupFileExtension, Home Manager refuses to replace an existing backup path unless home-manager.overwriteBackup is enabled:

{
  home-manager.backupFileExtension = "backup";
  home-manager.overwriteBackup = true;
}

Warning

home-manager.overwriteBackup allows activation to clobber existing backup files. Only enable it when those backup paths are disposable.

For individual files, many file options also support force = true:

{
  home.file.".config/example" = {
    source = ./example;
    force = true;
  };
}

This skips the collision check for the affected target and lets Home Manager replace the existing file or link. Use it sparingly; it can silently delete local changes.

Backup commands and backup extensions are intended for unmanaged non-symlink paths. If the colliding target is an unmanaged symbolic link, move it manually or use force = true after checking that the link target is safe to replace.

Advanced file behavior

The notes below apply to home.file and to options based on the same file type, such as xdg.configFile.

When a file source is a directory, home.file.<name>.recursive changes how the directory is linked. With the default recursive = false, the target is one symbolic link to the source directory. With recursive = true, Home Manager creates a matching directory tree and links each leaf file into it.

Recursive directory linking has special overlap behavior. A direct duplicate target, such as two managed files both targeting foo, is an error. If a recursively linked directory provides foo/bar and another managed file also targets foo/bar, Home Manager keeps the recursive file by default and ignores the overlapping regular file.

The home.file.<name>.onChange hook runs after the new files are linked. For recursive file entries, the hook is always run, so it should be written to be safe even when no leaf file actually changed.

Normally a path assigned to home.file.<name>.source is copied or linked through the Nix store. To make Home Manager create a link to a live path outside the store, use config.lib.file.mkOutOfStoreSymlink:

{ config, ... }:

{
  home.file.".config/example".source =
    config.lib.file.mkOutOfStoreSymlink ./example;
}

This is useful when the target should follow changes to a mutable file or directory outside the store.

Graphical services

Home Manager includes a number of services intended to run in a graphical session, for example xscreensaver and dunst. Unfortunately, such services will not be started automatically unless you let Home Manager start your X session. That is, you have something like

{
  # …

  services.xserver.enable = true;

  # …
}

in your system configuration and

{
  # …

  xsession.enable = true;
  xsession.windowManager.command = "…";

  # …
}

in your Home Manager configuration.

GPU on non-NixOS systems

When sudo is available: fixing the host OS
No root access: wrapping programs

To access the GPU, programs need access to OpenGL and Vulkan libraries. While this works transparently on NixOS, it does not on other Linux systems. There are two options:

Recommended: modify the host system slightly so that the graphics libraries can be found where programs from Nixpkgs can find them.

Wrap programs from Nixpkgs in an environment which tells them where to find graphics libraries.

The first option is very clean because the needed modifications to the host OS are small. However, it does require root/sudo access to the system, which may not be available. The second approach avoids that. However, it injects libraries from Nixpkgs into the environment of wrapped programs, which can make it impossible to launch programs of the host OS from wrapped programs.

When sudo is available: fixing the host OS

The targets.genericLinux.gpu module is automatically enabled whenever the option targets.genericLinux.enable is set (unless NixGL is used instead), which is recommended for non-NixOS Linux distributions in any case. The module can also be explicitly enabled by setting targets.genericLinux.gpu.enable.

This module builds a directory containing GPU libraries. When activating the home configuration by home-manager switch, the host system is examined: for compatibility with NixOS, these libraries need to be placed in /run/opengl-driver. If this directory does not exist, or contains a different set of libraries, the activation script will print a warning such as

Activating checkExistingGpuDrivers
GPU drivers require an update, run
  sudo /nix/store/HASH-non-nixos-gpu/bin/non-nixos-gpu-setup

Because the /run directory is volatile and disappears on reboot, libraries cannot be simply copied or linked there. The non-nixos-gpu-setup script installs a Systemd service which ensures that the drivers are linked to /run/opengl-driver on boot. Home Manager will always check and warn you when this setup needs to be refreshed.

If you ever wish to uninstall these drivers, all you need to do is

sudo rm /run/opengl-driver
sudo systemctl disable --now non-nixos-gpu.service
sudo rm /etc/systemd/system/non-nixos-gpu.service

GPU offloading

You can use the targets.genericLinux.nixGL.prime.installScript option. It installs the prime-offload script which is configured through options under targets.genericLinux.nixGL.prime. This functionality is independent from the rest of NixGL and can be used when targets.genericLinux.nixGL.packages is left null, which it should be when using drivers from /run/opengl-driver.

Nvidia drivers

If you need to include the proprietary Nvidia drivers, the process is a bit more involved. You need to:

Determine the exact version used by the host system. Example: 550.163.01

Fetch that version of the drivers from Nvidia and calculate their hash. Example:

nix store prefetch-file \
  https://download.nvidia.com/XFree86/Linux-x86_64/550.163.01/NVIDIA-Linux-x86_64-550.163.01.run

Attention: the version and architecture are present twice. If you are on an ARM system, replace x86_64 with aarch64.

Put this information into your home configuration. Example:

targets.genericLinux.gpu.nvidia = {
  enable = true;
  version = "550.163.01";
  sha256 = "sha256-74FJ9bNFlUYBRen7+C08ku5Gc1uFYGeqlIh7l1yrmi4=";
};

Warning

The Nvidia driver version must match the host system. This means that you must pay attention when upgrading the system and update the home configuration as well.

No root access: wrapping programs

The wrapping approach is facilitated by NixGL, which can be integrated into Home Manager.

Warning

This approach can cause issues when a wrapped program from Nixpkgs executes a program from the host. For example, Firefox from Nixpkgs must be wrapped by NixGL in order for graphical acceleration to work. If you then download a PDF file and open it in a PDF viewer that is not installed from Nixpkgs but is provided by the host distribution, there may be issues. Because Firefox’s environment injects libraries from NixGL, they are inherited by the PDF viewer, and unless they are the same or compatible version as the libraries on the host, the viewer will not work. This problem manifests more often with Vulkan because it needs a larger set of injected libraries than OpenGL.

The problem typically manifests with errors similar to

/nix/store/HASH-gcc-12.3.0-lib/lib/libstdc++.so.6: version `GLIBCXX_3.4.31' not found

To enable the integration, import NixGL into your home configuration, either as a channel, or as a flake input passed via extraSpecialArgs. Then, set the targets.genericLinux.nixGL.packages option to the package set provided by NixGL.

Once integration is enabled, it can be used in two ways: as Nix functions for wrapping programs installed via Home Manager, and as shell commands for running programs installed by other means (such as nix shell). In either case, there are several wrappers available. They can be broadly categorized

by vendor: as Mesa (for Free drivers of all vendors) and Nvidia (for Nvidia-specific proprietary drivers).

by GPU selection: as primary and secondary (offloading).

For example, the mesa wrapper provides support for running programs on the primary GPU for Intel, AMD and Nouveau drivers, while the mesaPrime wrapper does the same for the secondary GPU.

Note: when using Nvidia wrappers together with flakes, your home configuration will not be pure and needs to be built using home-manager switch --impure. Otherwise, the build will fail, complaining about missing attribute currentTime.

Wrapper functions are available under config.lib.nixGL.wrappers. However, it can be more convenient to use the config.lib.nixGL.wrap alias, which can be configured to use any of the wrappers. It is intended to provide a customization point when the same home configuration is used across several machines with different hardware. There is also the config.lib.nixGL.wrapOffload alias for two-GPU systems.

Another convenience is that all wrapper functions are always available. However, when targets.genericLinux.nixGL.packages option is unset, they are no-ops. This allows them to be used even when the home configuration is used on NixOS machines. The exception is the prime-offload script which ignores targets.genericLinux.nixGL.packages and is installed into the environment whenever targets.genericLinux.nixGL.prime.installScript is set. This script, which can be used to start a program on a secondary GPU, does not depend on NixGL and is useful on NixOS systems as well.

Below is an abbreviated example for an Optimus laptop that makes use of both Mesa and Nvidia wrappers, where the latter is used in dGPU offloading mode. It demonstrates how to wrap mpv to run on the integrated Intel GPU, wrap FreeCAD to run on the Nvidia dGPU, and how to install the wrapper scripts. It also wraps Xonotic to run on the dGPU, but uses the wrapper function directly for demonstration purposes.

{ config, lib, pkgs, nixgl, ... }:
{
  targets.genericLinux.nixGL = {
    packages = nixgl.packages;
    defaultWrapper = "mesa";
    offloadWrapper = "nvidiaPrime";
    installScripts = [ "mesa" "nvidiaPrime" ];
  };

  programs.mpv = {
    enable = true;
    package = config.lib.nixGL.wrap pkgs.mpv;
  };

  home.packages = [
    (config.lib.nixGL.wrapOffload pkgs.freecad)
    (config.lib.nixGL.wrappers.nvidiaPrime pkgs.xonotic)
  ];
}

The above example assumes a flake-based setup where nixgl was passed from the flake. When using channels, the example would instead begin with

{ config, lib, pkgs, ... }:
{
  targets.genericLinux.nixGL.packages = import <nixgl> { inherit pkgs; };
  # The rest is the same as above
  ...

Modular Services

Configuration data
Scope notes

Home Manager supports nixpkgs modular services under home.services. This is the home-manager analog to the NixOS system.services namespace: each entry is an abstract service sourced from <nixpkgs/lib/services/lib.nix> with the upstream portable systemd module loaded into it, so service modules shipped with packages (e.g. pkgs.<name>.passthru.services.default) drop in unchanged – the same module evaluates on NixOS and on Home Manager.

A minimal example – run a one-shot user service from a package’s modular service definition:

{ pkgs, ... }: {
  home.services.tunnel = {
    imports = [ pkgs.ghostunnel.passthru.services.default ];
    ghostunnel = {
      listen = "127.0.0.1:8443";
      target = "127.0.0.1:8080";
      cert = "/run/secrets/cert.pem";
      key = "/run/secrets/key.pem";
      allowAll = true;
    };
  };
}

This produces ~/.config/systemd/user/tunnel.service with the expected ExecStart, LoadCredential, and WantedBy=default.target.

Each service exposes the upstream NixOS-style schema: process.argv, systemd.lib, systemd.mainExecStart, systemd.service, systemd.services, systemd.sockets. Lifted units are translated from NixOS-style attrs (wantedBy, serviceConfig, unitConfig, environment, …) into the section-based INI shape ({ Unit; Service; Install; }) that home-manager’s systemd.user.services consumes. Only common keys are mapped explicitly; uncommon options remain reachable via unitConfig, serviceConfig, or socketConfig.

Sub-services (nested services.<sub> inside another service) and their units are dashed under the parent service name. The empty unit key "" denotes the service’s primary unit (lifted to a unit named after the service itself); process.argv becomes the default ExecStart for that unit, which defaults to WantedBy=default.target.

Configuration data

Each service can declare configuration files via configData.<name>. These are materialized at $XDG_CONFIG_HOME/system-services/<service>/<name> (mirroring how NixOS lifts configData to environment.etc), with the absolute path injected back into configData.<name>.path so the service can refer to its files at a stable location:

{ config, ... }:
{
  home.services.demo = {
    process.argv = [ "/bin/myapp" "--config" config.home.services.demo.configData."app.toml".path ];
    configData."app.toml".text = ''
      port = 1234
    '';
  };
}

Scope notes

Home Manager mirrors the surface of nixpkgs’ portable systemd module: services and sockets only. Other unit kinds Home Manager supports natively under systemd.user.services (timers, paths, mounts, …) are intentionally not modeled on home.services until upstream grows them, to keep both surfaces aligned.

Updating

Flake-Based Configurations
Channel-Based Configurations

Updating means moving to a newer revision of the Home Manager branch that your configuration already follows. For example, a configuration using release-25.11 can update to a newer revision of release-25.11 without changing release branches.

If you want to move from one release branch to another, such as release-25.05 to release-25.11, or between a release branch and master, see Upgrading to a new Home Manager release.

Flake-Based Configurations

Flake inputs are pinned in flake.lock, and Home Manager will keep using the pinned revisions until you update that lock file.

To update all inputs in the flake:

$ nix flake update

To update only specific inputs, name them explicitly:

$ nix flake update home-manager nixpkgs

These commands assume that your current directory is the flake. If not, pass the flake path or URI with --flake <flake-uri>.

After updating the lock file, rebuild with the command for your installation method.

For a standalone Home Manager flake:

$ home-manager switch --flake .

For Home Manager as a NixOS module:

$ sudo nixos-rebuild switch --flake .

For Home Manager as a nix-darwin module:

$ darwin-rebuild switch --flake .

Channel-Based Configurations

Channels are mutable references outside the Home Manager configuration itself. Updating a channel moves it to a newer revision of the same channel or branch.

For a standalone Home Manager channel installation, update the user’s channels and then switch:

$ nix-channel --update
…
unpacking channels...
$ home-manager switch

For Home Manager as a NixOS module, update the root user’s Home Manager channel and rebuild the system:

$ sudo nix-channel --update home-manager
$ sudo nixos-rebuild switch

For Home Manager as a nix-darwin module, update the Home Manager channel used by your nix-darwin configuration and rebuild the system:

$ nix-channel --update home-manager
$ darwin-rebuild switch

Upgrading to a new Home Manager release

Overview
Understanding Home Manager Versioning
Flake-Based Installation
Channel-Based Installation
State Version Management
Troubleshooting
Additional Resources

Overview

When moving your configuration to a new Nixpkgs release branch, you should also move Home Manager to the matching release branch. On NixOS this usually means upgrading Home Manager together with NixOS. On standalone and nix-darwin installations, match Home Manager to the Nixpkgs branch used by your configuration. The examples below use 25.11; replace this with the release branch you are upgrading to.

If your configuration follows nixos-unstable or nixpkgs-unstable, use Home Manager’s master branch.

Understanding Home Manager Versioning

Home Manager follows NixOS release cycles and provides corresponding branches:

release-<version>: Stable branch for the matching NixOS or Nixpkgs release, such as release-25.11.

master: Development branch (tracks nixos-unstable)

Note

Use the Home Manager branch that matches the Nixpkgs branch used to evaluate your Home Manager configuration. For stable NixOS configurations, this is normally the same as your NixOS version.

Flake-Based Installation

If you are using Home Manager with Nix flakes, update your nixpkgs and home-manager inputs together:

{
  description = "Home Manager configuration";

  inputs = {
    # Match the Nixpkgs branch to the release you are using.
    nixpkgs.url = "github:NixOS/nixpkgs/nixos-25.11";

    home-manager = {
      # Match the Home Manager branch to the Nixpkgs branch above.
      url = "github:nix-community/home-manager/release-25.11";
    };
  };

  outputs = { nixpkgs, home-manager, ... }: {
    homeConfigurations."yourusername" = home-manager.lib.homeManagerConfiguration {
      pkgs = nixpkgs.legacyPackages.x86_64-linux;
      modules = [ ./home.nix ];
    };
  };
}

For nixos-unstable or nixpkgs-unstable, use the master branch instead:

{
  inputs = {
    nixpkgs.url = "github:NixOS/nixpkgs/nixos-unstable";

    home-manager = {
      url = "github:nix-community/home-manager";
    };
  };
}

Then update the lock file and rebuild using the command for your installation method.

For a standalone Home Manager flake:

$ nix flake update
$ home-manager switch --flake .

For Home Manager as a NixOS module:

$ nix flake update
$ sudo nixos-rebuild switch --flake .

For Home Manager as a nix-darwin module:

$ nix flake update
$ darwin-rebuild switch --flake .

These commands assume that your current directory is the flake. If not, pass the flake path or URI with --flake <flake-uri>.

Channel-Based Installation

For a standalone channel-based installation, first verify your current Home Manager channel:

$ nix-channel --list

The entry identifies the Home Manager branch currently in use. For example:

home-manager https://github.com/nix-community/home-manager/archive/release-25.11.tar.gz

Update the Home Manager channel to the branch matching your Nixpkgs release, then switch:

$ nix-channel --add https://github.com/nix-community/home-manager/archive/release-25.11.tar.gz home-manager
$ nix-channel --update
$ home-manager switch

When Home Manager is installed as a NixOS module with channels, update the root user’s Home Manager channel and rebuild the system:

$ sudo nix-channel --add https://github.com/nix-community/home-manager/archive/release-25.11.tar.gz home-manager
$ sudo nix-channel --update
$ sudo nixos-rebuild switch

When Home Manager is installed as a nix-darwin module with channels, update the Home Manager channel used by your nix-darwin configuration and rebuild the system:

$ nix-channel --add https://github.com/nix-community/home-manager/archive/release-25.11.tar.gz home-manager
$ nix-channel --update
$ darwin-rebuild switch

State Version Management

Warning

Careful updating your home.stateVersion when upgrading Home Manager.

The stateVersion should remain set to the Home Manager release you first used for this home configuration.

{
  # Example: if this home configuration was first created on 24.11.
  home.stateVersion = "24.11";
}

Why? The stateVersion ensures backward compatibility and prevents breaking changes from affecting your existing configuration.

Remember: Channel or flake input version is not the same as state version. Update Home Manager, keep home.stateVersion unchanged, and only change it after reading the release notes and migrating any affected configuration.

Troubleshooting

Common Issues

Check the Home Manager Release Notes for breaking changes.

Version Mismatch Warning: If you see warnings about version mismatches, ensure your Home Manager branch matches the Nixpkgs branch used by your configuration. For NixOS stable releases, this usually means matching your NixOS version.

Module Changes: Modules are constantly being updated with new features to keep up with changes in upstream packaging or to fix bugs and add features. If you have an unexpected change, check if there was something noted in the release notes or news entries.

Channel Not Found: If nix-channel --list shows no channels, you might be using a different installation method, such as flakes, or Home Manager may be imported through your system configuration.

Verification

After upgrading, verify the installation:

$ home-manager --version

This should show the Home Manager version or indicate that it is using the expected release branch.

Additional Resources

NixOS Stable Release Notes

Home Manager Release Notes

Nix Flakes

Home Manager is compatible with Nix Flakes. But please be aware that this support is still experimental and may change in backwards incompatible ways.

Just like in the standard installation you can use the Home Manager flake in three ways:

Using the standalone home-manager tool. For platforms other than NixOS and Darwin, this is the only available choice. It is also recommended for people on NixOS or Darwin that want to manage their home directory independently of the system as a whole. See Standalone setup for instructions on how to perform this installation.

As a module within a NixOS system configuration. This allows the user profiles to be built together with the system when running nixos-rebuild. See NixOS module for a description of this setup.

As a module within a nix-darwin system configuration. This allows the user profiles to be built together with the system when running darwin-rebuild. See nix-darwin module for a description of this setup.

Advanced users may want Home Manager’s nixpkgs input to follow the same Nixpkgs input as the rest of their flake. This avoids a second Nixpkgs input and makes Home Manager use the same pinned Nixpkgs source revision as the rest of the configuration:

home-manager.inputs.nixpkgs.follows = "nixpkgs";

This removes the compatibility assumption between Home Manager and the Nixpkgs revision in Home Manager’s own lock file, so use it carefully, especially when tracking unstable branches.

This does not by itself make Home Manager use the same pkgs value as your NixOS or nix-darwin system. In NixOS and nix-darwin module setups, home-manager.useGlobalPkgs = true controls that behavior by making Home Manager modules receive the system pkgs value. When home-manager.useGlobalPkgs is enabled, configure Nixpkgs overlays and configuration at the system level instead of through Home Manager nixpkgs.* options.

Table of Contents

Prerequisites
Standalone setup
NixOS module
nix-darwin module
flake-parts module

Prerequisites

Install Nix 2.4 or later, or have it in nix-shell.

Enable experimental features nix-command and flakes.

When using NixOS, add the following to your configuration.nix and rebuild your system.

nix.settings.experimental-features = "nix-command flakes";

If you are not using NixOS, add the following to nix.conf (located at ~/.config/nix/ or /etc/nix/nix.conf).

experimental-features = nix-command flakes

You may need to restart the Nix daemon with, for example, sudo systemctl restart nix-daemon.service.

Alternatively, you can enable flakes on a per-command basis with the following additional flags to nix and home-manager:

$ nix --extra-experimental-features "nix-command flakes" <sub-commands>
$ home-manager --extra-experimental-features "nix-command flakes" <sub-commands>

Prepare your Home Manager configuration (home.nix).

Unlike the channel-based setup, home.nix will be evaluated when the flake is built, so it must be present before bootstrap of Home Manager from the flake. See Configuration Example for introduction about writing a Home Manager configuration.

Standalone setup

To prepare an initial Home Manager configuration for your logged in user, you can run the Home Manager init command directly from its flake.

For example, if you are using the unstable version of Nixpkgs or NixOS, then to generate and activate a basic configuration run the command

$ nix run home-manager/master -- init --switch

For Nixpkgs or NixOS version 25.11 run

$ nix run home-manager/release-25.11 -- init --switch

This will generate a flake.nix and a home.nix file in ~/.config/home-manager, creating the directory if it does not exist.

If you need to pass additional values from your flake to home.nix or any imported Home Manager modules, use extraSpecialArgs in the call to home-manager.lib.homeManagerConfiguration:

{
  inputs = {
    nixpkgs.url = "github:nixos/nixpkgs/nixos-unstable";
    home-manager.url = "github:nix-community/home-manager";
  };

  outputs = inputs@{ nixpkgs, home-manager, ... }: {
    homeConfigurations.jdoe = home-manager.lib.homeManagerConfiguration {
      pkgs = nixpkgs.legacyPackages.x86_64-linux;
      extraSpecialArgs = { inherit inputs; };
      modules = [ ./home.nix ];
    };
  };
}

Any attribute in extraSpecialArgs becomes a module argument, so home.nix or imported modules can declare arguments such as { inputs, ... }:.

The lower-level mechanism behind this is _module.args. Set _module.args.<name> from inside a module only when you need to provide a module argument from within the module graph itself. For values that originate outside the module graph, such as flake inputs, prefer extraSpecialArgs.

If you omit the --switch option then the activation will not happen. This is useful if you want to inspect and edit the configuration before activating it.

$ nix run home-manager/$branch -- init
$ # Edit files in ~/.config/home-manager
$ nix run home-manager/$branch -- init --switch

Where $branch is one of master or release-25.11.

After the initial activation has completed successfully then building and activating your flake-based configuration is as simple as

$ home-manager switch

It is possible to override the default configuration directory, if you want. For example,

$ nix run home-manager/$branch -- init --switch ~/hmconf
$ # And after the initial activation.
$ home-manager switch --flake ~/hmconf

Note

The flake inputs are not automatically updated by Home Manager. Update the lock file with nix flake update before switching if you want to use newer input revisions.

If you only want to update specific flake inputs, name them explicitly, for example nix flake update nixpkgs home-manager.

These commands assume that your current directory is the flake. If not, pass the flake path or URI with --flake <flake-uri>.

NixOS module

To use Home Manager as a NixOS module, a bare-minimum flake.nix would be as follows:

{
  description = "NixOS configuration";

  inputs = {
    nixpkgs.url = "github:nixos/nixpkgs/nixos-unstable";
    home-manager.url = "github:nix-community/home-manager";
  };

  outputs = inputs@{ nixpkgs, home-manager, ... }: {
    nixosConfigurations = {
      hostname = nixpkgs.lib.nixosSystem {
        system = "x86_64-linux";
        modules = [
          ./configuration.nix
          home-manager.nixosModules.home-manager
          {
            home-manager.useGlobalPkgs = true;
            home-manager.useUserPackages = true;
            home-manager.extraSpecialArgs = { inherit inputs; };
            home-manager.users.jdoe = ./home.nix;
          }
        ];
      };
    };
  };
}

Use home-manager.extraSpecialArgs to pass arguments from your flake to home.nix and any imported Home Manager modules. For example, the configuration above makes the complete inputs attrset available to modules, so they can declare arguments such as { inputs, ... }:.

The lower-level mechanism behind this is _module.args. Set _module.args.<name> from inside a module only when you need to provide a module argument from within the module graph itself. For values that originate outside the module graph, such as flake inputs, prefer home-manager.extraSpecialArgs.

The Home Manager configuration is then part of the NixOS configuration and is automatically rebuilt with the system when using the appropriate command for the system, such as

$ nixos-rebuild switch --flake /etc/nixos

You can use the above flake.nix as a template in /etc/nixos by

$ nix flake new /etc/nixos -t github:nix-community/home-manager#nixos

nix-darwin module

The flake-based setup of the Home Manager nix-darwin module is similar to that of NixOS. The flake.nix would be:

{
  description = "Darwin configuration";

  inputs = {
    nixpkgs.url = "github:nixos/nixpkgs/nixos-unstable";
    darwin.url = "github:nix-darwin/nix-darwin";
    darwin.inputs.nixpkgs.follows = "nixpkgs";
    home-manager.url = "github:nix-community/home-manager";
  };

  outputs = inputs@{ nixpkgs, home-manager, darwin, ... }: {
    darwinConfigurations = {
      hostname = darwin.lib.darwinSystem {
        system = "x86_64-darwin";
        modules = [
          ./configuration.nix
          home-manager.darwinModules.home-manager
          {
            home-manager.useGlobalPkgs = true;
            home-manager.useUserPackages = true;
            home-manager.extraSpecialArgs = { inherit inputs; };
            home-manager.users.jdoe = ./home.nix;
          }
        ];
      };
    };
  };
}

Use home-manager.extraSpecialArgs to pass arguments from your flake to home.nix and any imported Home Manager modules. For example, the configuration above makes the complete inputs attrset available to modules, so they can declare arguments such as { inputs, ... }:.

The lower-level mechanism behind this is _module.args. Set _module.args.<name> from inside a module only when you need to provide a module argument from within the module graph itself. For values that originate outside the module graph, such as flake inputs, prefer home-manager.extraSpecialArgs.

and it is also rebuilt with the nix-darwin generations. The rebuild command here may be darwin-rebuild switch --flake ~/.config/darwin.

You can use the above flake.nix as a template in ~/.config/darwin by

$ nix flake new ~/.config/darwin -t github:nix-community/home-manager#nix-darwin

flake-parts module

When using flake-parts you may wish to import Home Manager’s flake module, flakeModules.home-manager.

{
  description = "flake-parts configuration";

  inputs = {
    nixpkgs.url = "github:nixos/nixpkgs/nixos-unstable";
    home-manager.url = "github:nix-community/home-manager";
    flake-parts.url = "github:hercules-ci/flake-parts";
  };

  outputs = inputs@{
    flake-parts,
    home-manager,
    nixpkgs,
    ...
  }:
    flake-parts.lib.mkFlake { inherit inputs; } {
      imports = [
        # Import home-manager's flake module
        inputs.home-manager.flakeModules.home-manager
      ];
      flake = {
        # Reusable Home Manager module.
        homeModules.bash= { pkgs, ... }: {
          programs.bash = {
            enable = true;
            shellAliases = {
              ll = "ls -l";
            };
          };
          home.packages = [ pkgs.hello ];
        };

        # Concrete Home Manager configuration.
        homeConfigurations.alice = home-manager.lib.homeManagerConfiguration {
          pkgs = import nixpkgs { system = "x86_64-linux"; };
          modules = [
            inputs.self.homeModules.bash
            {
              home.username = "alice";
              home.homeDirectory = "/home/alice";
              home.stateVersion = "25.11";
            }
          ];
        };
      };
      # See flake.parts for more features, such as `perSystem`
    };
}

The flake module defines the flake.homeModules and flake.homeConfigurations options, allowing them to be properly merged if they are defined in multiple modules.

If you are only defining homeModules and/or homeConfigurations once in a single module, flake-parts should work fine without importing flakeModules.home-manager.

Writing Home Manager Modules

The module system in Home Manager is based entirely on the NixOS module system so we will here only highlight aspects that are specific for Home Manager. For information about the module system as such please refer to the Writing NixOS Modules chapter of the NixOS manual.

Table of Contents

Option Types

Option Types

Overall the basic option types are the same in Home Manager as NixOS. A few Home Manager options, however, make use of custom types that are worth describing in more detail. These are the option types dagOf and gvariant that are used, for example, by programs.ssh.matchBlocks and dconf.settings.

hm.types.dagOf

Options of this type have attribute sets as values where each member is a node in a directed acyclic graph (DAG). This allows the attribute set entries to express dependency relations among themselves. This can, for example, be used to control the order of match blocks in a OpenSSH client configuration or the order of activation script blocks in home.activation.

A number of functions are provided to create DAG nodes. The functions are shown below with examples using an option foo.bar of type hm.types.dagOf types.int.

hm.dag.entryAnywhere (value: T) : DagEntry<T>

Indicates that value can be placed anywhere within the DAG. This is also the default for plain attribute set entries, that is

foo.bar = {
  a = hm.dag.entryAnywhere 0;
}

and

foo.bar = {
  a = 0;
}

are equivalent.

hm.dag.entryAfter (afters: list string) (value: T) : DagEntry<T>

Indicates that value must be placed after each of the attribute names in the given list. For example

foo.bar = {
  a = 0;
  b = hm.dag.entryAfter [ "a" ] 1;
}

would place b after a in the graph.

hm.dag.entryBefore (befores: list string) (value: T) : DagEntry<T>

Indicates that value must be placed before each of the attribute names in the given list. For example

foo.bar = {
  b = hm.dag.entryBefore [ "a" ] 1;
  a = 0;
}

would place b before a in the graph.

hm.dag.entryBetween (befores: list string) (afters: list string) (value: T) : DagEntry<T>

Indicates that value must be placed before the attribute names in the first list and after the attribute names in the second list. For example

foo.bar = {
  a = 0;
  c = hm.dag.entryBetween [ "b" ] [ "a" ] 2;
  b = 1;
}

would place c before b and after a in the graph.

There are also a set of functions that generate a DAG from a list. These are convenient when you just want to have a linear list of DAG entries, without having to manually enter the relationship between each entry. Each of these functions take a tag as argument and the DAG entries will be named ${tag}-${index}.

hm.dag.entriesAnywhere (tag: string) (values: [T]) : Dag<T>

Creates a DAG with the given values with each entry labeled using the given tag. For example

foo.bar = hm.dag.entriesAnywhere "a" [ 0 1 ];

is equivalent to

foo.bar = {
  a-0 = 0;
  a-1 = hm.dag.entryAfter [ "a-0" ] 1;
}

hm.dag.entriesAfter (tag: string) (afters: list string) (values: [T]) : Dag<T>

Creates a DAG with the given values with each entry labeled using the given tag. The list of values are placed are placed after each of the attribute names in afters. For example

foo.bar =
  { b = 0; }
  // hm.dag.entriesAfter "a" [ "b" ] [ 1 2 ];

is equivalent to

foo.bar = {
  b = 0;
  a-0 = hm.dag.entryAfter [ "b" ] 1;
  a-1 = hm.dag.entryAfter [ "a-0" ] 2;
}

hm.dag.entriesBefore (tag: string) (befores: list string) (values: [T]) : Dag<T>

Creates a DAG with the given values with each entry labeled using the given tag. The list of values are placed before each of the attribute names in befores. For example

foo.bar =
  { b = 0; }
  // hm.dag.entriesBefore "a" [ "b" ] [ 1 2 ];

is equivalent to

foo.bar = {
  b = 0;
  a-0 = 1;
  a-1 = hm.dag.entryBetween [ "b" ] [ "a-0" ] 2;
}

hm.dag.entriesBetween (tag: string) (befores: list string) (afters: list string) (values: [T]) : Dag<T>

Creates a DAG with the given values with each entry labeled using the given tag. The list of values are placed before each of the attribute names in befores and after each of the attribute names in afters. For example

foo.bar =
  { b = 0; c = 3; }
  // hm.dag.entriesBetween "a" [ "b" ] [ "c" ] [ 1 2 ];

is equivalent to

foo.bar = {
  b = 0;
  c = 3;
  a-0 = hm.dag.entryAfter [ "c" ] 1;
  a-1 = hm.dag.entryBetween [ "b" ] [ "a-0" ] 2;
}

hm.types.gvariant

This type is useful for options representing GVariant values. The type accepts all primitive GVariant types as well as arrays, tuples, “maybe” types, and dictionaries.

Some Nix values are automatically coerced to matching GVariant value but the GVariant model is richer so you may need to use one of the provided constructor functions. Examples assume an option foo.bar of type hm.types.gvariant.

hm.gvariant.mkBoolean (v: bool)

Takes a Nix value v to a GVariant boolean value (GVariant format string b). Note, Nix booleans are automatically coerced using this function. That is,

foo.bar = hm.gvariant.mkBoolean true;

is equivalent to

foo.bar = true;

hm.gvariant.mkString (v: string)

Takes a Nix value v to a GVariant string value (GVariant format string s). Note, Nix strings are automatically coerced using this function. That is,

foo.bar = hm.gvariant.mkString "a string";

is equivalent to

foo.bar = "a string";

hm.gvariant.mkObjectpath (v: string)

Takes a Nix value v to a GVariant objectpath value (GVariant format string o).

hm.gvariant.mkUchar (v: string)

Takes a Nix value v to a GVariant uchar value (GVariant format string y).

hm.gvariant.mkInt16 (v: int)

Takes a Nix value v to a GVariant int16 value (GVariant format string n).

hm.gvariant.mkUint16 (v: int)

Takes a Nix value v to a GVariant uint16 value (GVariant format string q).

hm.gvariant.mkInt32 (v: int)

Takes a Nix value v to a GVariant int32 value (GVariant format string i). Note, Nix integers are automatically coerced using this function. That is,

foo.bar = hm.gvariant.mkInt32 7;

is equivalent to

foo.bar = 7;

hm.gvariant.mkUint32 (v: int)

Takes a Nix value v to a GVariant uint32 value (GVariant format string u).

hm.gvariant.mkInt64 (v: int)

Takes a Nix value v to a GVariant int64 value (GVariant format string x).

hm.gvariant.mkUint64 (v: int)

Takes a Nix value v to a GVariant uint64 value (GVariant format string t).

hm.gvariant.mkDouble (v: double)

Takes a Nix value v to a GVariant double value (GVariant format string d). Note, Nix floats are automatically coerced using this function. That is,

foo.bar = hm.gvariant.mkDouble 3.14;

is equivalent to

foo.bar = 3.14;

hm.gvariant.mkArray type elements

Builds a GVariant array containing the given list of elements, where each element is a GVariant value of the given type (GVariant format string a${type}). The type value can be constructed using

hm.gvariant.type.string (GVariant format string s)

hm.gvariant.type.boolean (GVariant format string b)

hm.gvariant.type.uchar (GVariant format string y)

hm.gvariant.type.int16 (GVariant format string n)

hm.gvariant.type.uint16 (GVariant format string q)

hm.gvariant.type.int32 (GVariant format string i)

hm.gvariant.type.uint32 (GVariant format string u)

hm.gvariant.type.int64 (GVariant format string x)

hm.gvariant.type.uint64 (GVariant format string t)

hm.gvariant.type.double (GVariant format string d)

hm.gvariant.type.variant (GVariant format string v)

hm.gvariant.type.arrayOf type (GVariant format string a${type})

hm.gvariant.type.maybeOf type (GVariant format string m${type})

hm.gvariant.type.tupleOf types (GVariant format string (${lib.concatStrings types}))

hm.gvariant.type.dictionaryEntryOf [keyType valueType] (GVariant format string {${keyType}${valueType}})

where type and types are themselves a type and list of types, respectively.

hm.gvariant.mkEmptyArray type

An alias of hm.gvariant.mkArray type [].

hm.gvariant.mkNothing type

Builds a GVariant maybe value (GVariant format string m${type}) whose (non-existent) element is of the given type. The type value is constructed as described for the mkArray function above.

hm.gvariant.mkJust element

Builds a GVariant maybe value (GVariant format string m${element.type}) containing the given GVariant element.

hm.gvariant.mkTuple elements

Builds a GVariant tuple containing the given list of elements, where each element is a GVariant value.

hm.gvariant.mkVariant element

Builds a GVariant variant (GVariant format string v) which contains the value of a GVariant element.

hm.gvariant.mkDictionaryEntry [key value]

Builds a GVariant dictionary entry containing the given list of elements (GVariant format string {${key.type}${value.type}}), where each element is a GVariant value.

Contributing

Contributions to Home Manager are very welcome. To make the process as smooth as possible for both you and the Home Manager maintainers we provide some guidelines that we ask you to follow. See Getting started for information on how to set up a suitable development environment and Guidelines for the actual guidelines.

This text is mainly directed at those who would like to make code contributions to Home Manager. If you just want to report a bug then first look among the already open issues, if you find one matching yours then feel free to comment on it to add any additional information you may have. If no matching issue exists then go to the new issue page and write a description of your problem. Include as much information as you can, ideally also include relevant excerpts from your Home Manager configuration.

Table of Contents

Getting started
Guidelines
News
Tests

Getting started

If you have not previously forked Home Manager then you need to do that first. Have a look at GitHub’s Fork a repo for instructions on how to do this.

Once you have a fork of Home Manager you should create a branch starting at the most recent master branch. Give your branch a reasonably descriptive name. Commit your changes to this branch and when you are happy with the result and it fulfills Guidelines then push the branch to GitHub and create a pull request.

Assuming your clone is at $HOME/devel/home-manager then you can make the home-manager command use it by either

overriding the default path by using the -I command line option:

$ home-manager -I home-manager=$HOME/devel/home-manager

or, if using flakes:

$ home-manager --override-input home-manager ~/devel/home-manager

or

changing the default path by ensuring your configuration includes

programs.home-manager.enable = true;
programs.home-manager.path = "$HOME/devel/home-manager";

and running home-manager switch to activate the change. Afterwards, home-manager build and home-manager switch will use your cloned repository.

The first option is good if you only temporarily want to use your clone.

Guidelines

Maintain backward compatibility
Keep forward compatibility in mind
Add only valuable options
Add relevant tests
Add relevant documentation
Module Auto-importing
Add yourself as a module maintainer
Format your code
Format your commit messages
Format your news entries
Use conditional modules and news
Mind the license
Commits
Example commit
Code Style

If your contribution satisfy the following rules then there is a good chance it will be merged without too much trouble. The rules are enforced by the Home Manager maintainers and to a lesser extent the Home Manager CI system.

If you are uncertain how these rules affect the change you would like to make then feel free to start a discussion in the #home-manager IRC channel, ideally before you start developing.

Maintain backward compatibility

Your contribution should not cause another user’s existing configuration to break unless there is a very good reason and the change should be announced to the user through an assertion or similar.

Remember that Home Manager is used in many different environments and you should consider how your change may effect others. For example,

Does your change work for people that do not use NixOS? Consider other GNU/Linux distributions and macOS.

Does your change work for people whose configuration is built on one system and deployed on another system?

Keep forward compatibility in mind

The master branch of Home Manager tracks the unstable channel of Nixpkgs, which may update package versions at any time. It is therefore important to consider how a package update may affect your code and try to reduce the risk of breakage.

The most effective way to reduce this risk is to follow the advice in Add only valuable options.

Add only valuable options

When creating a new module it is tempting to include every option supported by the software. This is strongly discouraged. Providing many options increases maintenance burden and risk of breakage considerably. This is why only the most important software options should be modeled explicitly. Less important options should be expressible through an extraConfig escape hatch.

A good rule of thumb for the first implementation of a module is to only add explicit options for those settings that absolutely must be set for the software to function correctly. It follows that a module for software that provides sensible default values for all settings would require no explicit options at all.

If the software uses a structured configuration format like a JSON, YAML, INI, TOML, or even a plain list of key/value pairs then consider using a settings option as described in Nix RFC 42.

Add relevant tests

If at all possible, make sure to add new tests and expand existing tests so that your change will keep working in the future. See Tests for more information about the Home Manager test suite.

All contributed code must pass the test suite.

Add relevant documentation

Many code changes require changing the documentation as well. The documentation is written in Nixpkgs-flavoured Markdown. All text is hosted in Home Manager’s Git repository.

The HTML version of the manual containing both the module option descriptions and the documentation of Home Manager can be generated and opened by typing the following in a shell within a clone of the Home Manager Git repository:

$ nix-build -A docs.html
$ xdg-open ./result/share/doc/home-manager/index.xhtml

When you have made changes to a module, it is a good idea to check that the man page version of the module options looks good:

$ nix-build -A docs.manPages
$ man ./result/share/man/man5/home-configuration.nix.5.gz

Module Auto-importing

Home Manager automatically imports all modules from the modules/programs/ and modules/services/ directories. This auto-importing behavior follows these rules:

Nix files: All .nix files in these directories are automatically imported

Directories: All subdirectories are automatically imported (typically containing a default.nix file)

Exclusions: Files and directories starting with an underscore (_) are excluded from auto-importing

This allows for flexible module organization:

modules/programs/
├── git.nix              # Single-file module (imported)
├── firefox/             # Multi-file module (imported)
│   ├── default.nix
│   └── addons.nix
├── _experimental.nix    # Excluded (starts with _)
└── _wip/                # Excluded directory (starts with _)
    └── newfeature.nix

When adding a new module, simply place it in the appropriate directory (programs/ for user programs, services/ for user services) and it will be automatically discovered and included in the Home Manager module system.

Add yourself as a module maintainer

Every new module must include a named maintainer using the meta.maintainers attribute. If you are a user of a module that currently lacks a maintainer then please consider adopting it.

If you are present in the nixpkgs maintainer list then you can use that entry. If you are not then you can add yourself to modules/lib/maintainers.nix in the Home Manager project.

As a maintainer you are expected to respond to issues and pull-requests associated with your module.

Maintainers are encouraged to join the IRC or Matrix channel and participate when they have opportunity.

Format your code

Make sure your code is formatted as described in Code Style. To maintain consistency throughout the project you are encouraged to browse through existing code and adopt its style also in new code.

Format your commit messages

Similar to Format your code we encourage a consistent commit message format as described in Commits.

Format your news entries

If your contribution includes a change that should be communicated to users of Home Manager then you can add a news entry. The entry must be formatted as described in News.

When new modules are added a news entry should be included.

Use conditional modules and news

Home Manager includes a number of modules that are only usable on some of the supported platforms. The most common example of platform specific modules are those that define systemd user services, which only works on Linux systems.

If you add a module that is platform specific then make sure to include a condition in the loadModule function call. This will make the module accessible only on systems where the condition evaluates to true.

Similarly, if you are adding a news entry then it should be shown only to users that may find it relevant, see News for a description of conditional news.

Mind the license

The Home Manager project is covered by the MIT license and we can only accept contributions that fall under this license, or are licensed in a compatible way. When you contribute self written code and documentation it is assumed that you are doing so under the MIT license.

A potential gotcha with respect to licensing are option descriptions. Often it is convenient to copy from the upstream software documentation. When this is done it is important to verify that the license of the upstream documentation allows redistribution under the terms of the MIT license.

Commits

The commits in your pull request should be reasonably self-contained, that is, each commit should make sense in isolation. In particular, you will be asked to amend any commit that introduces syntax errors or similar problems even if they are fixed in a later commit.

The commit messages should follow the seven rules, except for "Capitalize the subject line". We also ask you to include the affected code component or module in the first line. That is, a commit message should follow the template

{component}: {description}

{long description}

where {component} refers to the code component (or module) your change affects, {description} is a very brief description of your change, and {long description} is an optional clarifying description. As a rare exception, if there is no clear component, or your change affects many components, then the {component} part is optional. See example_title for a commit message that fulfills these requirements.

Example commit

The commit 69f8e47e9e74c8d3d060ca22e18246b7f7d988ef contains the commit message

    starship: allow running in Emacs if vterm is used

    The vterm buffer is backed by libvterm and can handle Starship prompts
    without issues.

which ticks all the boxes necessary to be accepted in Home Manager.

Finally, when adding a new module, say programs/foo.nix, we use the fixed commit format foo: add module. You can, of course, still include a long description if you wish.

Code Style

The code in Home Manager is formatted by the treefmt tool and the formatting is checked in the pull request tests. Run nix fmt or treefmt (with required formatters which can be found in treefmt.toml in your $PATH) inside the project repository before submitting your pull request.

Keep lines at a reasonable width, ideally 80 characters or less. This also applies to string literals.

We prefer lowerCamelCase for variable and attribute names with the accepted exception of variables directly referencing packages in Nixpkgs which use a hyphenated style. For example, the Home Manager option services.gpg-agent.enableSshSupport references the gpg-agent package in Nixpkgs.

News

Home Manager includes a system for presenting news to the user. When making a change you, therefore, have the option to also include an associated news entry. In general, a news entry should only be added for truly noteworthy news. For example, a bug fix or new option does generally not need a news entry.

If you do have a change worthy of a news entry then please add one in news.nix but you should follow some basic guidelines:

Use the included news entry generator to create a news entry file:

$ nix run .#create-news-entry

Alternatively, you can directly use the script:

$ nix-shell -A dev --run modules/misc/news/create-news-entry.sh

This will create a new file inside the modules/misc/news directory with some placeholder information that you can edit.

The entry condition should be as specific as possible. For example, if you are changing or deprecating a specific option then you could restrict the news to those users who actually use this option.

Wrap the news message so that it will fit in the typical terminal, that is, at most 80 characters wide. Ideally a bit less.

Unlike commit messages, news will be read without any connection to the Home Manager source code. It is therefore important to make the message understandable in isolation and to those who do not have knowledge of the Home Manager internals. To this end it should be written in more descriptive, prose like way.

If you refer to an option then write its full attribute path. That is, instead of writing

The option 'foo' has been deprecated, please use 'bar' instead.

it should read

The option 'services.myservice.foo' has been deprecated, please
use 'services.myservice.bar' instead.

A new module, say foo.nix, should always include a news entry that has a message along the lines of

A new module is available: 'services.foo'.

If the module is platform specific, e.g., a service module using systemd, then a condition like

condition = hostPlatform.isLinux;

should be added. If you contribute a module then you don’t need to add this entry, the merger will create an entry for you.

Tests

Writing Basic Tests
Using the tests command
Manual test commands

Home Manager includes a basic test suite and it is highly recommended to include at least one test when adding a module. Tests are typically in the form of "golden tests" where, for example, a generated configuration file is compared to a known correct file.

It is relatively easy to create tests by modeling the existing tests, found in the tests project directory.

Writing Basic Tests

Home Manager tests use the NMT framework, which provides a set of assertion functions to verify that modules generate the expected files and configurations. Tests are written as Nix expressions that define both the Home Manager configuration and the test assertions.

Test Structure

A basic test file structure looks like:

{
  # Home Manager configuration
  programs.myprogram = {
    enable = true;
    settings = {
      option = "value";
    };
  };

  # NMT test script with assertions
  nmt.script = ''
    assertFileExists "home-files/.config/myprogram/config.toml"
    assertFileContent "home-files/.config/myprogram/config.toml" ${./expected-config.toml}
  '';
}

Test Organization

Tests are organized in the tests directory structure:

tests/modules/programs/myprogram/default.nix - Lists all test cases for the module

tests/modules/programs/myprogram/basic-configuration.nix - A basic test case

tests/modules/programs/myprogram/expected-config.toml - Expected output file

The default.nix file should list all test cases:

{
  myprogram-basic-configuration = ./basic-configuration.nix;
  myprogram-empty-settings = ./empty-settings.nix;
}

Common NMT Assertions

NMT provides several assertion functions:

assertFileExists "path" - Verify a file was created

assertPathNotExists "path" - Verify a file was NOT created

assertFileContent "path" expected-file - Compare file contents

assertFileRegex "path" "regex" - Check file matches regex

For a full reference to the functions available in test scripts, you can look at NMT’s bash-lib.

Practical Examples

Here are some real-world examples of common test patterns:

Testing that a configuration file is generated:

{
  programs.alacritty = {
    enable = true;
    settings.font.size = 12;
  };

  nmt.script = ''
    assertFileExists "home-files/.config/alacritty/alacritty.yml"
    assertFileContains "home-files/.config/alacritty/alacritty.yml" "size: 12"
  '';
}

Testing that no files are created when disabled:

{
  programs.alacritty.enable = false;

  nmt.script = ''
    assertPathNotExists "home-files/.config/alacritty"
  '';
}

Testing exact file content against expected output:

{
  programs.fastfetch = {
    enable = true;
    settings.display.color = "blue";
  };

  nmt.script =
    let
      configFile = "home-files/.config/fastfetch/config.jsonc";
    in
    ''
      assertFileExists "${configFile}"
      assertFileContent "${configFile}" ${./expected-config.jsonc}
    '';
}

Testing multiple conditions in one test:

{
  programs.myprogram = {
    enable = true;
    configFile = "custom.conf";
    extraConfig = "debug = true";
  };

  nmt.script = ''
    assertFileExists "home-files/.config/myprogram/custom.conf"
    assertFileRegex "home-files/.config/myprogram/custom.conf" "debug = true"
    assertFileRegex "home-files/.config/myprogram/custom.conf" "^# Generated by Home Manager"
  '';
}

Platform-Specific Tests

When a module is platform-specific (Linux-only or Darwin-only), the test’s default.nix file should use lib.optionalAttrs to conditionally expose tests based on the platform. This prevents evaluation errors on unsupported platforms during the test suite runs.

Linux-only module tests:

{ lib, pkgs, ... }:

lib.optionalAttrs pkgs.stdenv.hostPlatform.isLinux {
  rofi-valid-config = ./valid-config.nix;
  rofi-custom-theme = ./custom-theme.nix;
}

Darwin-only module tests:

{ lib, pkgs, ... }:

lib.optionalAttrs pkgs.stdenv.hostPlatform.isDarwin {
  sketchybar-basic = ./basic-configuration.nix;
  sketchybar-lua-config = ./lua-config.nix;
}

For cross-platform modules that have packages which need to be stubbed on Darwin, add the package names to tests/darwinScrublist.nix to prevent build failures during cross-platform test runs.

Using the tests command

Home Manager provides a convenient tests command for discovering and running tests:

# List all available tests
$ nix run .#tests -- -l

# List tests matching a pattern
$ nix run .#tests -- -l alacritty

# Run all tests matching a pattern
$ nix run .#tests -- alacritty

# Run a specific test
$ nix run .#tests -- test-alacritty-empty-settings

# Run integration tests
$ nix run .#tests -- -t -l

# Interactive test selection (requires fzf)
$ python3 tests/tests.py -i

# Pass additional nix build flags
$ nix run .#tests -- alacritty -- --verbose

Manual test commands

For advanced usage or CI environments, you can also run tests manually using nix build commands.

The full Home Manager test suite can be run by executing

$ nix-build --pure --option allow-import-from-derivation false tests -A build.all

in the project root. List all test cases through

$ nix-build --pure tests --option allow-import-from-derivation false -A list

and run an individual test, for example alacritty-empty-settings, through

$ nix-build --pure tests --option allow-import-from-derivation false -A build.alacritty-empty-settings

However, those invocations will impurely source the system’s Nixpkgs, and may cause failures. To run against the Nixpkgs from the flake.lock file, use instead e.g.

$ nix build --option allow-import-from-derivation false .#test-all

or

$ nix build --option allow-import-from-derivation false .#test-alacritty-empty-settings

Some tests may be marked with enableLegacyIfd, those may be run by run with e.g.

$ nix-build --pure tests --arg enableLegacyIfd true -A build.mytest

Home Manager Internals

This chapter collects some documentation about the internal workings of Home Manager. The information here is mostly aimed to developers of Home Manager and those who do non-trivial integration with Home Manager.

Table of Contents

Activation

Activation

Activating a Home Manager configuration ensures that the built configuration is introduced into the user’s environment. The activation is performed by a suitably named script activate. This script is generated as part of the configuration build and is placed in the root of the build output.

The activation script is implemented in the Bash language and consists of initialization code followed by a number of activation script blocks. These blocks are specified using the home.activation option. The blocks may have dependencies among themselves and the generated activation script will contain the blocks serialized such that the dependencies are satisfied. A dependency cycle causes a failure when the configuration is built.

Historically, the activation script has been responsible for creating a new generation of the home-manager Nix profile. The more modern way, however, is to let the activation driver – that is, the software calling the activation script – manage the profile. Indeed, in some cases we may not have a home-manager profile at all! This is the case when Home Manager is used as a NixOS or nix-darwin module, in these cases the system profile will contain references to the corresponding Home Manager configurations.

Note, to maintain backwards compatibility, the old activation script behavior is still the default. To choose the new mode of operation you have to call the activation script with the command line option --driver-version 1. The old behavior is available using --driver-version 0, or simply omit it entirely.

Unfortunately, driver software need to support both modes of operation for the time being since a user may wish to activate an old generation that contains an activation script that does not support --driver-version. To determine whether support is available, check the gen-version file in the configuration build output root. If the file is missing then the activation script does not support --driver-version. If the file exists and contains the integer 1 or higher, then --driver-version 1 is supported.

Third-Party Tools and Extensions

Here is a collection of tools and extensions that relate to Home Manager. Note, these are maintained outside the regular Home Manager flow so quality and support may vary wildly. If you encounter problems then please raise them in the corresponding project, not as issues in the Home Manager tracker.

If you have made something interesting related to Home Manager then you are encouraged to create a PR that expands this chapter.

Table of Contents

Module Collections

Module Collections

xhmm — extra Home Manager modules

A collection of modules maintained by Anselm Schüler.

Stylix — System-wide colorscheming and typography

Configure your applications to get coherent color scheme and font.

Frequently Asked Questions (FAQ)

Table of Contents

Why is there a collision error when switching generation?
Why are the session variables not set?
How to set up a configuration for multiple users/machines?
Why do I get an error message about ca.desrt.dconf or dconf.service?
How do I install packages from Nixpkgs unstable?
How do I change the package used by a module?

Why is there a collision error when switching generation?

Home Manager currently installs packages into the user environment, precisely as if the packages were installed through nix-env --install. This means that you will get a collision error if your Home Manager configuration attempts to install a package that you already have installed manually, that is, packages that shows up when you run nix-env --query.

For example, imagine you have the hello package installed in your environment

$ nix-env --query
hello-2.10

and your Home Manager configuration contains

home.packages = [ pkgs.hello ];

Then attempting to switch to this configuration will result in an error similar to

$ home-manager switch
these derivations will be built:
  /nix/store/xg69wsnd1rp8xgs9qfsjal017nf0ldhm-home-manager-path.drv
[…]
Activating installPackages
replacing old ‘home-manager-path’
installing ‘home-manager-path’
building path(s) ‘/nix/store/b5c0asjz9f06l52l9812w6k39ifr49jj-user-environment’
Wide character in die at /nix/store/64jc9gd2rkbgdb4yjx3nrgc91bpjj5ky-buildenv.pl line 79.
collision between ‘/nix/store/fmwa4axzghz11cnln5absh31nbhs9lq1-home-manager-path/bin/hello’ and ‘/nix/store/c2wyl8b9p4afivpcz8jplc9kis8rj36d-hello-2.10/bin/hello’; use ‘nix-env --set-flag priority NUMBER PKGNAME’ to change the priority of one of the conflicting packages
builder for ‘/nix/store/b37x3s7pzxbasfqhaca5dqbf3pjjw0ip-user-environment.drv’ failed with exit code 2
error: build of ‘/nix/store/b37x3s7pzxbasfqhaca5dqbf3pjjw0ip-user-environment.drv’ failed

The solution is typically to uninstall the package from the environment using nix-env --uninstall and reattempt the Home Manager generation switch.

You could also opt to uninstall all of the packages from your profile with nix-env --uninstall '*'.

Why are the session variables not set?

Home Manager is only able to set session variables automatically if it manages your Bash, Z shell, or fish shell configuration. To enable such management you use programs.bash.enable, programs.zsh.enable, or programs.fish.enable.

If you don’t want to let Home Manager manage your shell then you will have to manually source the ~/.nix-profile/etc/profile.d/hm-session-vars.sh file in an appropriate way. In Bash and Z shell this can be done by adding

. "$HOME/.nix-profile/etc/profile.d/hm-session-vars.sh"

to your .profile and .zshrc files, respectively. The hm-session-vars.sh file should work in most Bourne-like shells. For fish shell, it is possible to source it using the foreign-env plugin or using the builtin babelfish-translated variables:

fenv source "$HOME/.nix-profile/etc/profile.d/hm-session-vars.sh" > /dev/null
# or
source "$HOME/.nix-profile/etc/profile.d/hm-session-vars.fish"

How to set up a configuration for multiple users/machines?

A typical way to prepare a repository of configurations for multiple logins and machines is to prepare one "top-level" file for each unique combination.

For example, if you have two machines, called "kronos" and "rhea" on which you want to configure your user "jane" then you could create the files

kronos-jane.nix,

rhea-jane.nix, and

common.nix

in your repository. On the kronos and rhea machines you can then make ~jane/.config/home-manager/home.nix be a symbolic link to the corresponding file in your configuration repository.

The kronos-jane.nix and rhea-jane.nix files follow the format

{ ... }:

{
  imports = [ ./common.nix ];

  # Various options that are specific for this machine/user.
}

while the common.nix file contains configuration shared across the two logins. Of course, instead of just a single common.nix file you can have multiple ones, even one per program or service.

You can get some inspiration from the Post your home-manager home.nix file! Reddit thread.

Why do I get an error message about ca.desrt.dconf or dconf.service?

You are most likely trying to configure something that uses dconf but the DBus session is not aware of the dconf service. The full error you might get is

error: GDBus.Error:org.freedesktop.DBus.Error.ServiceUnknown: The name ca.desrt.dconf was not provided by any .service files

or

error: GDBus.Error:org.freedesktop.systemd1.NoSuchUnit: Unit dconf.service not found.

The solution on NixOS is to add

programs.dconf.enable = true;

to your system configuration.

How do I install packages from Nixpkgs unstable?

If you are using a stable version of Nixpkgs but would like to install some particular packages from Nixpkgs unstable – or some other channel – then you can import the unstable Nixpkgs and refer to its packages within your configuration.

With channels, something like

{ pkgs, config, ... }:

let
  pkgsUnstable = import <nixpkgs-unstable> {};
in
{
  home.packages = [
    pkgsUnstable.foo
  ];
  # …
}

should work provided you have a Nix channel called nixpkgs-unstable.

You can add the nixpkgs-unstable channel by running

$ nix-channel --add https://nixos.org/channels/nixpkgs-unstable nixpkgs-unstable
$ nix-channel --update

With flakes, add another Nixpkgs input and pass its packages to your Home Manager modules. For example, a standalone Home Manager flake can define the following. Replace 25.11 with the release branch your configuration follows.

{
  inputs = {
    nixpkgs.url = "github:NixOS/nixpkgs/nixos-25.11";
    nixpkgs-unstable.url = "github:NixOS/nixpkgs/nixpkgs-unstable";
    home-manager.url = "github:nix-community/home-manager/release-25.11";
  };

  outputs =
    { nixpkgs, nixpkgs-unstable, home-manager, ... }:
    let
      # Replace this with the system of your Home Manager configuration.
      system = "x86_64-linux";
      pkgs = nixpkgs.legacyPackages.${system};
      pkgsUnstable = nixpkgs-unstable.legacyPackages.${system};
    in
    {
      homeConfigurations.jdoe = home-manager.lib.homeManagerConfiguration {
        inherit pkgs;
        extraSpecialArgs = { inherit pkgsUnstable; };
        modules = [ ./home.nix ];
      };
    };
}

and then use the extra argument in home.nix:

{ pkgsUnstable, ... }:

{
  home.packages = [
    pkgsUnstable.foo
  ];
}

When Home Manager is used as a NixOS or nix-darwin module, pass the extra package set with home-manager.extraSpecialArgs in the system configuration:

outputs =
  { nixpkgs, nixpkgs-unstable, home-manager, ... }:
  let
    # Replace this with the system of your NixOS or nix-darwin configuration.
    system = "x86_64-linux";
  in
  {
    nixosConfigurations.hostname = nixpkgs.lib.nixosSystem {
      inherit system;
      modules = [
        home-manager.nixosModules.home-manager
        ({ config, ... }: {
          home-manager.extraSpecialArgs = {
            pkgsUnstable = import nixpkgs-unstable {
              inherit system;
              config = config.nixpkgs.config;
              overlays = config.nixpkgs.overlays;
            };

            # If you use a stock Nixpkgs configuration, you can use:
            # pkgsUnstable = nixpkgs-unstable.legacyPackages.${system};
          };
        })
      ];
    };
  };

The nix-darwin setup is the same pattern with darwin.lib.darwinSystem and home-manager.darwinModules.home-manager.

How do I change the package used by a module?

By default Home Manager will install the package provided by your chosen nixpkgs channel but occasionally you might end up needing to change this package. This can typically be done in two ways.

If the module provides a package option, such as programs.beets.package, then this is the recommended way to perform the change. For example,

programs.beets.package = pkgs.beets.override { pluginOverrides = { beatport.enable = false; }; };

See Nix pill 17 for more information on package overrides. Alternatively, if you want to use the beets package from Nixpkgs unstable, then a configuration like

{ pkgs, config, ... }:

let
  pkgsUnstable = import <nixpkgs-unstable> {};
in
{
  programs.beets.package = pkgsUnstable.beets;

  # …
}

should work OK. With flakes, pass the unstable package set as described in How do I install packages from Nixpkgs unstable? and then use the extra module argument:

{ pkgsUnstable, ... }:

{
  programs.beets.package = pkgsUnstable.beets;

  # …
}

If no package option is available then you can typically change the relevant package using an overlay.

For example, if you want to use the programs.skim module but use the skim package from Nixpkgs unstable, then a configuration like

{ pkgs, config, ... }:

let
  pkgsUnstable = import <nixpkgs-unstable> {};
in

{
  programs.skim.enable = true;

  nixpkgs.overlays = [
    (_final: _prev: {
      skim = pkgsUnstable.skim;
    })
  ];

  # …
}

should work OK.

The same Home Manager overlay works in a flake-based standalone configuration if pkgsUnstable is passed to the Home Manager module:

{ pkgsUnstable, ... }:

{
  programs.skim.enable = true;

  nixpkgs.overlays = [
    (_final: _prev: {
      skim = pkgsUnstable.skim;
    })
  ];

  # …
}

This also works when Home Manager is used as a NixOS or nix-darwin module without home-manager.useGlobalPkgs = true. If home-manager.useGlobalPkgs = true is enabled, Home Manager uses the system package set and the nixpkgs.* options inside Home Manager are disabled. In that case, put the overlay in the system configuration instead, for example:

{ pkgsUnstable, ... }:

{
  nixpkgs.overlays = [
    (_final: _prev: {
      skim = pkgsUnstable.skim;
    })
  ];
}

In a flake-based NixOS or nix-darwin configuration, pass pkgsUnstable to nixosSystem or darwinSystem with specialArgs.

  |   |  Next
  |   |  Appendix A. Home Manager Configuration Options